<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sargent Reading Group Notes</title>
    <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Sargent Reading Group Notes</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-EN</language>
    <managingEditor>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</webMaster>
    <copyright>(c) 2015 Spencer Lyon.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 08 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://srg.spencerlyon.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Begenau, Farboodi, and Veldkamp (2018) (Big Data in Finance and the Growth of Large Firms.)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2018/05/08/begenau-farboodi-and-veldkamp-2018-big-data-in-finance-and-the-growth-of-large-firms./</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2018/05/08/begenau-farboodi-and-veldkamp-2018-big-data-in-finance-and-the-growth-of-large-firms./</guid>
      <description>This paper studies the hypothesis that the use of big data sets and technologies by financial firms has lowered the cost of capital for large firms, relative to small ones, allowing large firms to grow larger.
The authors motivate the study of the growth rate of small and large firms by noting that in terms of employment and revenue share, the firms in the top 5% have grown more and faster relative to small firms.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Athreya, Owens, and Schwartzman (2017) (Does redistribution increase output? The centrality of labor supply.)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2018/04/24/athreya-owens-and-schwartzman-2017-does-redistribution-increase-output-the-centrality-of-labor-supply./</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2018/04/24/athreya-owens-and-schwartzman-2017-does-redistribution-increase-output-the-centrality-of-labor-supply./</guid>
      <description>The goal of this paper is to understand what impacts a redistribution from rich to poor has on short run output. The authors want to understand the mechanisms or model assumptions that lead to quantitatively significant effects.
The standard thinking is that a transfer from rich to poor will stimulate the economy, because in general the poor have a higher marginal propensity to consume out of wealth. The main finding of this paper is that this line of thinking is only correct and significant</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dolandson and Hornbeck (2016) (Railroads and American Economic Growth: A “Market Access” Approach)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2018/04/17/dolandson-and-hornbeck-2016-railroads-and-american-economic-growth-a-market-access-approach/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2018/04/17/dolandson-and-hornbeck-2016-railroads-and-american-economic-growth-a-market-access-approach/</guid>
      <description>This paper studies how the growth of the railroad infrastructure in the US between 1870 and 1890 changed the “market access” each county had to all other US counties and the implications for this change in market access on the value of agricultural land.
Data In this time period, there were three primary modes of transportation (for moving freight):
Roads travelled via wagon Canals travelled via barge Railroads  The dataset used in this paper has three main components:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Atkin, Khandelwal, Osman (2017). (Exporting and Firm Performance: Evidence from a Randomized Experiment)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2018/04/10/atkin-khandelwal-osman-2017.-exporting-and-firm-performance-evidence-from-a-randomized-experiment/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2018/04/10/atkin-khandelwal-osman-2017.-exporting-and-firm-performance-evidence-from-a-randomized-experiment/</guid>
      <description>This paper uses a randomized empirical experiment to address how much exporting impacts firm performance. Tens of billions of dollars are spent each year by organizations like the world trade organization in an effort to help developing countries participate in global export markets. One justification for this spending is that people believe that exporting improves firm productivity through learning-by-exporting. When learning-by-exporting happens, trade generates efficiency gains that narrow the productivity gap and further magnify gains from trade.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Athey (2018). (The Impact of Machine Learning on Economics)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2018/04/03/athey-2018.-the-impact-of-machine-learning-on-economics/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2018/04/03/athey-2018.-the-impact-of-machine-learning-on-economics/</guid>
      <description>This is what I’ll call an editorial paper where someone in economics that uses many tools and ideas from machine learning surveys the current usages of ML in econ and muses about the possible future interactions between the two fields.
There isn’t a whole lot of meat here in terms of model or data, but there are interesting concepts that I think will be applicable to empirical economists in the future.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bergemann, Bonatti, and Smolin (2018). (The Design and Price of Information.)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2018/03/27/bergemann-bonatti-and-smolin-2018.-the-design-and-price-of-information./</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2018/03/27/bergemann-bonatti-and-smolin-2018.-the-design-and-price-of-information./</guid>
      <description>This paper analyzes a theoretical framework for thinking about how information can be productized and priced.
Model This is a static, one-shot model.
There are two agents: a decision maker or data buyer, and a data seller.
There a finite number of states and a finite number of actions available to the decision maker.
The true state is hidden to the data buyer. The data buyer receives utility based on the realized state and action she chooses.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Steinwender (2018) (Real Effects of Information Frictions: When the States and the Kingdom Became United)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2018/03/20/steinwender-2018-real-effects-of-information-frictions-when-the-states-and-the-kingdom-became-united/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2018/03/20/steinwender-2018-real-effects-of-information-frictions-when-the-states-and-the-kingdom-became-united/</guid>
      <description>This author uses data from just before and after the trans Atlantic telegraph was completed to study how information frictions distorted international trade in cotton between the US and the United Kingdom.
Data This paper uses from July 29, 1865 through July 27, 1867. The telegraph was completed in July 28, 1866 – 1/2 of the sample is before the telegraph and 1/2 is after.
At the time, the primary route for cotton trade was between New York City and Liverpool England.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Doraszelski, Lewis, Pakes (2018) (Just Starting Out: Learning And Equilibrium In A New Market)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2018/03/13/doraszelski-lewis-pakes-2018-just-starting-out-learning-and-equilibrium-in-a-new-market/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2018/03/13/doraszelski-lewis-pakes-2018-just-starting-out-learning-and-equilibrium-in-a-new-market/</guid>
      <description>This paper uses legal reform in the energy industry in the UK as a natural experiment to study how firms learn to compete and optimally set prices while converging to behavior that looks like competitive Nash equilibrium.
TODO: revise the last few words. Nash what exactly?
Electricity in the UK The paper goes into very interesting detail about how the electricity collection and delivery happens in the UK. I’ll do my best to cover the essential parts here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Grossman and Helpman 2018 (Growth, Trade, and Inequality)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2018/02/27/grossman-and-helpman-2018-growth-trade-and-inequality/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2018/02/27/grossman-and-helpman-2018-growth-trade-and-inequality/</guid>
      <description>The contribution of this paper is a model of how growth and wage inequality can be co-determined in equilibrium. The model is studied in both closed economy and international trade settings. We will focus on the closed economy description of the model and briefly mention the implications of having two copies of this economy interact in labor and product markets.
Model Environment Infinite horizon, discrete time. One country that operates two sectors: research (idea creation) and production (idea using).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Brynjolfsson and Hitt 2003</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2018/02/13/brynjolfsson-and-hitt-2003/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2018/02/13/brynjolfsson-and-hitt-2003/</guid>
      <description>CLOSED: [2017-11-13 Mon 09:37]
Data The goal of this paper is to use firm-level data to determine the determinants of productivity and output growth.
To do this, the authors use a nearly-balanced panel from 1987-1994 on 527 of the fortune 1000 firms to attempt to estimate the impact on investment in computers on output and productivity growth. This panel is a merging of compustat data with data from the Computer Intelligence InfoCorp, or CII.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Brynjolfsson and Hitt 2003 (Computing Productivity: Firm-Level Evidence)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2018/02/13/brynjolfsson-and-hitt-2003-computing-productivity-firm-level-evidence/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2018/02/13/brynjolfsson-and-hitt-2003-computing-productivity-firm-level-evidence/</guid>
      <description>Data The goal of this paper is to use firm-level data to determine the determinants of productivity and output growth.
To do this, the authors use a nearly-balanced panel from 1987-1994 on 527 of the fortune 1000 firms to attempt to estimate the impact on investment in computers on output and productivity growth. This panel is a merging of compustat data with data from the Computer Intelligence InfoCorp, or CII. The CII surveys the IT managers at the largest firms in the US at least frequency, but up to monthly based on the value of computer equipment installed at the firm.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Christiano, Motto, and Rostagno (2014) (Risk shocks)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2018/01/30/christiano-motto-and-rostagno-2014-risk-shocks/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2018/01/30/christiano-motto-and-rostagno-2014-risk-shocks/</guid>
      <description>Model The model in this paper is a mashup of the DSGE framework of Cristiano, Eichenbaum, and Evans and the entrepreneur and financial friction component of Bernanke, Gertler, and Gilchrist. To this framework they add an additional feature they term a “risk shock”, which is stochastic volatility in the distribution of entrepreneur productivity.
The model has too many pieces for me to describe in detail, so I will attempt to focus on the parts that are most important for understanding the key takeaway of the paper.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Eisfeldt and Papanikolaou (2013) (Organization capital and the cross section of expected returns)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/12/05/eisfeldt-and-papanikolaou-2013-organization-capital-and-the-cross-section-of-expected-returns/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/12/05/eisfeldt-and-papanikolaou-2013-organization-capital-and-the-cross-section-of-expected-returns/</guid>
      <description>Intro This paper studies subset of intangible capital called organizational capital. The authors define organizational capital as intangible capital embodied in the firm’s key employees
The authors maintain the hypothesis that returns from organizational capital are partly firm specific and partly due to key talent at the firm. Thus, shareholders must split revenues between themselves and key talent to entice them not to take their talents to another firm. This has a number of consequences:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Eisfeldt and Papanikolaou 2013</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/eisfeldt_papanikolaou_2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Nov 2017 09:41:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/eisfeldt_papanikolaou_2017/</guid>
      <description>1 Intro  IN RECENT DECADES, INTANGIBLE capital has become an increasingly important factor of production. In many instances, such intangible capital is embodied in the firm’s key employees. We refer to this type of intangible capital as organization capital and develop a structural model to analyze its effect on asset prices. We argue that shareholders consider firms with high levels of organization capital to be riskier than firms with more physical capital, and provide empirical evidence supporting this claim.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Eisfeldt and Papanikolaou 2013</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/11/30/eisfeldt-and-papanikolaou-2013/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Nov 2017 09:41:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/11/30/eisfeldt-and-papanikolaou-2013/</guid>
      <description>Intro  IN RECENT DECADES, INTANGIBLE capital has become an increasingly important factor of production. In many instances, such intangible capital is embodied in the firm’s key employees. We refer to this type of intangible capital as organization capital and develop a structural model to analyze its effect on asset prices. We argue that shareholders consider firms with high levels of organization capital to be riskier than firms with more physical capital, and provide empirical evidence supporting this claim.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>McGratten (2017) (Intangible Capital and Measured Productivity)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/11/28/mcgratten-2017-intangible-capital-and-measured-productivity/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/11/28/mcgratten-2017-intangible-capital-and-measured-productivity/</guid>
      <description>McGratten starts by saying that firms invest almost as much in intangible capital as they do physical capital, but that intangible capital is not reported in GDP. This severely understates the actual change in output. She sees this as one way in which we can see a rise in labor and investment coincide with relatively little increase in measured total factor productivity.
The goal of the paper is to build a multi-sector general equilibrium model that incorporates intangible capital and investment.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hall 1999 (The stock market and capital accumulation.)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/11/14/hall-1999-the-stock-market-and-capital-accumulation./</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/11/14/hall-1999-the-stock-market-and-capital-accumulation./</guid>
      <description>In this paper Hall seeks to quantify the price and stock of capital in the economy from 1960 to 2000 using data from the stock market.
To do this he proposes the following simple model.
 Discrete time, infinite horizon Constant returns to scale production All produciton inputs except capital adjust frictionlessly Adjustment to capital stock can be fully adjusted in the long run (no long run rents) Factor markets are competitive  In this setting firm profits is equal to capital times the product of capital, where the product of capital depends on non-capital production inputs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>De Loecker and Eeckhout (2017) (The Rise of Market Power and the Macroeconomic Implications)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/11/07/de-loecker-and-eeckhout-2017-the-rise-of-market-power-and-the-macroeconomic-implications/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/11/07/de-loecker-and-eeckhout-2017-the-rise-of-market-power-and-the-macroeconomic-implications/</guid>
      <description>This is a “facts” paper that documents some facts about the distribution of market power over time and then talks about some macroeconomic implications of the change in market power. To talk about some of these facts, they need to write down a very simple model.
Facts Data They use firm-level Compustat data from 1950-2014. The data includes all publicly traded firms over that time horizon. They comment that while this clearly does not include all firms, it does capture most of subset of firms relative for their study (large firms are usually public, and they are the ones with significant market power).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Asturias, Hur, Kehoe, and Ruhl (2017) (Firm Entry and Exit and Aggregate Growth.)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/10/24/asturias-hur-kehoe-and-ruhl-2017-firm-entry-and-exit-and-aggregate-growth./</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/10/24/asturias-hur-kehoe-and-ruhl-2017-firm-entry-and-exit-and-aggregate-growth./</guid>
      <description>This goal of this paper is to better understand how firm entry and exit interact with aggregate productivity growth.
Empirical finding The authors main empirical finding is that the contribution to aggregate productivity growth from new firms is larger in periods of high productivity growth than in periods of low productivity growth.
This finding is established using data on all manufacturing plants in Chile from 1995 to 2006 and in Korea for 1992-1997, 2001-2006, and 2009-2014.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lee and Yi (2017) (Global Value Chains and Inequality with Endogenous Labor Supply)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/10/17/lee-and-yi-2017-global-value-chains-and-inequality-with-endogenous-labor-supply/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/10/17/lee-and-yi-2017-global-value-chains-and-inequality-with-endogenous-labor-supply/</guid>
      <description>The goal of this paper is to use the modeling concept of Global value chains to analyze the international impact of a lowering of trade costs.
Model Most of the paper is about describing the model. It is too complicated to explain in full in just 5 minutes, so I will discuss some of the key features so we can understand the results.
The model is static.
There are N countries that are symmetric in technology, but will have different parameter values in the calibrated model.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lee and Yi (2017) (Global Value Chains and Inequality with Endogenous Labor Supply)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/10/17/lee-and-yi-2017-global-value-chains-and-inequality-with-endogenous-labor-supply/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/10/17/lee-and-yi-2017-global-value-chains-and-inequality-with-endogenous-labor-supply/</guid>
      <description>The goal of this paper is to use the modeling concept of Global value chains to analyze the international impact of a lowering of trade costs.
Model Most of the paper is about describing the model. It is too complicated to explain in full in just 5 minutes, so I will discuss some of the key features so we can understand the results.
The model is static.
There are N countries that are symmetric in technology, but will have different parameter values in the calibrated model.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Heathcote, Storesletten, and Violante (2017) (Optimal tax progressivity: An analytical framework)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/10/03/heathcote-storesletten-and-violante-2017-optimal-tax-progressivity-an-analytical-framework/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/10/03/heathcote-storesletten-and-violante-2017-optimal-tax-progressivity-an-analytical-framework/</guid>
      <description>The goal of this paper is to supply a theory that can shed light on what determines both the actual degree of tax progressivity in the US economy as well as a theoretical optimal level of tax progressivity.
Tax function The tax function used in this paper comes from Benabou (2002) and is log linear in income. That is taxes collected gross income, minus λ times gross income to the 1 − τ.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Antras, de Gortari, Itskhoki (2017) (Globalization, Inequality, and welfare)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/09/26/antras-de-gortari-itskhoki-2017-globalization-inequality-and-welfare/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/09/26/antras-de-gortari-itskhoki-2017-globalization-inequality-and-welfare/</guid>
      <description>The goal of this paper is to quantify the welfare implications of opening to trade in a setting where trade increases aggregate income, but also increases income inequality. Furthermore, redistribution happens through distorting income taxes.
Closed economy model Discrete time, infinite horizon.
A continuum of consumers, each with GHH preferences over an aggregate consumption good and labor. Individuals are indexed by their ability to produce a certain variety or task (unique to each consumer).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ljungqvist and Sargent (2011) (A Labor Supply Elasticity Accord?.)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/09/12/ljungqvist-and-sargent-2011-a-labor-supply-elasticity-accord./</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/09/12/ljungqvist-and-sargent-2011-a-labor-supply-elasticity-accord./</guid>
      <description>Here Ljungqvist and Sargent explain both sides of a long debated issue regarding labor supply elasticity (percent change in labor supply divided by percent change in wages) and then describe a relatively new idea that has the potential to reconcile the opposing views. The main argument from the micro-and-labor-economics camp is that the labor supply elasticity is quite low for individuals in the work force. On the other hand, macroeconomists typically say that the aggregate labor supply elasticity is large.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Autor, Dorn, Hanson, and Song (2014) (Trade Adjustment: Worker Level Evidence)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/05/02/autor-dorn-hanson-and-song-2014-trade-adjustment-worker-level-evidence/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/05/02/autor-dorn-hanson-and-song-2014-trade-adjustment-worker-level-evidence/</guid>
      <description>Empirical paper that tries to determine labor market response to China trade shock at the individual level. It is a complement to the authors’ China Syndrome paper that answers similar questions at the regional level.
Stylized facts To prompt their research, the authors list a number of recent stylized facts concerning China’s impact on US labor markets. They are that greater import exposure results in
 Higher rates of plant exit and more rapid declines in plant employment Larger decreases in manufacturing employment Increases in unemployment and labor force non-participation rates  These facts have been verified or reproduced at the industry and regional level, but the gap that this paper seeks to fill is what are the associated facts at the individual level.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Greenland, Lopresti, McHenry (2016) (Import Competition and Internal Migration)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/04/25/greenland-lopresti-mchenry-2016-import-competition-and-internal-migration/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/04/25/greenland-lopresti-mchenry-2016-import-competition-and-internal-migration/</guid>
      <description>This is a purely empirical paper that tries to determine the degree to which there was worker relocation across regions in the US in response to the Chinese trade shock.
Many recent papers have documented negative regional labor market consequences in regions that specialize in industries that are more exposed to Chinese trade competition. Among these results are higher unemployment, lower wages, and lower labor force participation rates. Furthermore, evidence has been presented showing that there was little to no contemporaneous worker migration out of exposed regions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Galle, Rodriguez-Clare, and  Yi (2015) (Slicing the pie: Quantifying the aggregate and distributional effects of trade)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/03/07/galle-rodriguez-clare-and--yi-2015-slicing-the-pie-quantifying-the-aggregate-and-distributional-effects-of-trade/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/03/07/galle-rodriguez-clare-and--yi-2015-slicing-the-pie-quantifying-the-aggregate-and-distributional-effects-of-trade/</guid>
      <description>This paper develops a model that allows the authors to assess the aggregate gains from trade and the distribution of the gains from trade across groups of workers.
The motivation for the paper came from a recognition that most empirical work focuses on the losses accrued on the import side from increased competition. The general equilibrium setup in this paper captures both import and export effects of trade shocks, which they use to paint a more complete picture of the distribution of welfare responses to trade exposure.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Autor, Dorn, and Hanson (2016) (The China Shock: Learning from Labor-Market Adjustment to Large Changes in Trade)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/02/28/autor-dorn-and-hanson-2016-the-china-shock-learning-from-labor-market-adjustment-to-large-changes-in-trade/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/02/28/autor-dorn-and-hanson-2016-the-china-shock-learning-from-labor-market-adjustment-to-large-changes-in-trade/</guid>
      <description>Review paper that summarizes the main points of the story behind China’s fantastic growth in export markets in the lats 30 years and how it has impacted labor markets of developed countries.
This paper covers a width breadth of material in relatively little depth, so I will pick and choose from the main points they tried to make.
The story  Mao Zedong founded People’s republic of China and governed it as the chairman of the communist part of China from 1949 until his death in 1976.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Drozd &amp; Nozal(2012) (Understanding International Prices: Customers as Capital)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/02/28/drozd--nozal2012-understanding-international-prices-customers-as-capital/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/02/28/drozd--nozal2012-understanding-international-prices-customers-as-capital/</guid>
      <description>This paper builds a model that treats consumers as a form of non-productive capital in an attempt to resolve a few outstanding puzzles in the international macro literature.
Puzzles The puzzles are:
In the standard theory (like BKK), the price of exported goods co-moves negatively with the price of imported goods. In their sample o2 12 OECD countries, the authors find that the correlation is always positive and covers a range from 0.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Barrot, Loualiche, Plosser, Sauvangnat (2016) (Import Competition and Household Debt)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/02/21/barrot-loualiche-plosser-sauvangnat-2016-import-competition-and-household-debt/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/02/21/barrot-loualiche-plosser-sauvangnat-2016-import-competition-and-household-debt/</guid>
      <description>Empirical paper that tries to quantify the effect of import competition on the composition of the balance sheet of individuals between 2000 and 2007.
The main finding is that consumers in regions with higher exposure to import competition had debt growth of 20 percentage points more than consumers in regions with low import competition exposure.
Data  New york FRB consumer credit panel: 5% of all US individuals with a credit record and social security number.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Benhabib, Perla, Tonetti (2017) (Reconciling Models of Diffusion and Innovation: A Theory of the Productivity Distribution and Technology Frontier.)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/02/14/benhabib-perla-tonetti-2017-reconciling-models-of-diffusion-and-innovation-a-theory-of-the-productivity-distribution-and-technology-frontier./</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/02/14/benhabib-perla-tonetti-2017-reconciling-models-of-diffusion-and-innovation-a-theory-of-the-productivity-distribution-and-technology-frontier./</guid>
      <description>The main contribution of this paper is to provide a model where technology adoption and innovation interact to determine the equilibrium characteristics of the economy.
They end up using a model where adoption an the rate of innovation are both choice variables for the firm, but describe the main mechanisms and intuitions where only adoption is a control variable and innovation is stochastic. The qualitative results from both models are the same, so I to will use the simpler model with exogenous innovation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Faber, Fally (2017) (Firm Heterogeneity in Consumption Baskets -- Evidence from Home and Store Scanner Data.)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/02/07/faber-fally-2017-firm-heterogeneity-in-consumption-baskets----evidence-from-home-and-store-scanner-data./</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/02/07/faber-fally-2017-firm-heterogeneity-in-consumption-baskets----evidence-from-home-and-store-scanner-data./</guid>
      <description>This paper considers the relation between of firm size heterogeneity and income dispersion. Using two large panel data sets, they document a number of empirical facts about the link between these forms of heterogeneity, then build a model combining non-homothetic preferences for consumers and a Metliz’ style production environment that can match the facts.
Data Kilts Nielsen consumer panel and retail scanner data..
 weekly upc code level data from households and firms contains prices and quantities also demographic info about households: discrete income binning, location Metadata about stores: brands they sell, location  Empirical finding Main empirical finding is that wealthier households spend a higher share of consumption expenditure on goods from large firms.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Y Yedid-Levi, S Haller, and D Fitzgerald (2017) (How Exporters Grow)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/01/31/y-yedid-levi-s-haller-and-d-fitzgerald-2017-how-exporters-grow/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/01/31/y-yedid-levi-s-haller-and-d-fitzgerald-2017-how-exporters-grow/</guid>
      <description>The authors of this paper use confidential Irish data to document 4 novel facts about the lifecycle of exporting firms and then combine two existing modeling pieces to builds a partial equilibrium model that can reconcile the reported facts.
Data The authors use two confidential micro data sets from Ireland:
The Irish census of industrial production Irish custom records  They are able to link the datasets to build a panel dataset at the firm-product-destination market level.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lustig, Zhang, and Hartman-Glaser (2016) (Capital Share Dynamics When Firms Insure Managers)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/12/13/lustig-zhang-and-hartman-glaser-2016-capital-share-dynamics-when-firms-insure-managers/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/12/13/lustig-zhang-and-hartman-glaser-2016-capital-share-dynamics-when-firms-insure-managers/</guid>
      <description>This paper uses Compustat data to document that the aggregate capital share of income and average capital share of income have diverged over the last 20 years. Specifically, the average capital share has fallen while the aggregate share has risen.
They then write down a model that uses changes in firm level volatility of productivity to generate similar dynamics in general equilibrium.
The model is interesting in its own right. It features a 2 sided limited commitment contracting problem.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Timoshenko (2015) (Learning, prices, and firm dynamics)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/12/06/timoshenko-2015-learning-prices-and-firm-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/12/06/timoshenko-2015-learning-prices-and-firm-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>The authors of this paper use firm level data on Portuguese manufacturing firms and documents two new novel facts about the joint evolution of firm performance and prices:
Within product categories, firms with longer tenure in export markets tend to export larger quantities at similar prices Older or more experienced exporters tend to import more expensive inputs  The authors then write down a model that can match these facts</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hess:2000wh (Risk sharing by households within and across regions and industries. (Hess, Shin; 2000))</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/11/22/hess2000wh-risk-sharing-by-households-within-and-across-regions-and-industries.-hess-shin-2000/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/11/22/hess2000wh-risk-sharing-by-households-within-and-across-regions-and-industries.-hess-shin-2000/</guid>
      <description>The goal of this paper is to test the degree of risk sharing across regions and industries in the US.
The rough outline is to write down a simple model they use to motivate an empirical specification, then test if that specification holds in the data.
Model There are H households that each live in one of R regions and work within one of I industries. Each period, households receive an endowment of the consumption good and are able to trade in complete state contingent markets.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adam:2011ix (Adam, K., &amp; Marcet, A. (2011). Internal rationality, imperfect market
knowledge and asset prices
)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/11/01/adam2011ix-adam-k.--marcet-a.-2011.-internal-rationality-imperfect-marketknowledge-and-asset-prices/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/11/01/adam2011ix-adam-k.--marcet-a.-2011.-internal-rationality-imperfect-marketknowledge-and-asset-prices/</guid>
      <description>The basic idea in this paper is to separate the standard rationality requirements embedded in the rational expectations hypothesis into internal and external components. Internal rationality means that the agents make fully optimal decisions given some well-defined subjective beliefs about payoff relevant variables. External rationality requires that the probability distribution generated by agent subjective beliefs matches the true distribution of underlying variables.
This paper will maintain the assumption of internal rationality, but not impose external rationality.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adam:2011ix (Adam, K., &amp; Marcet, A. (2011). Internal rationality, imperfect market knowledge and asset prices)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/11/01/adam2011ix-adam-k.--marcet-a.-2011.-internal-rationality-imperfect-market-knowledge-and-asset-prices/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/11/01/adam2011ix-adam-k.--marcet-a.-2011.-internal-rationality-imperfect-market-knowledge-and-asset-prices/</guid>
      <description>The basic idea in this paper is to separate the standard rationality requirements embedded in the rational expectations hypothesis into internal and external components. Internal rationality means that the agents make fully optimal decisions given some well-defined subjective beliefs about payoff relevant variables. External rationality requires that the probability distribution generated by agent subjective beliefs matches the true distribution of underlying variables.
This paper will maintain the assumption of internal rationality, but not impose external rationality.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adam:2016hd (Adam, K., &amp; Marcet, A. &amp; Nicolini J. (2016). Stock Market Volatility and Learning.)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/11/01/adam2016hd-adam-k.--marcet-a.--nicolini-j.-2016.-stock-market-volatility-and-learning./</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/11/01/adam2016hd-adam-k.--marcet-a.--nicolini-j.-2016.-stock-market-volatility-and-learning./</guid>
      <description>Builds on the internal rationality framework from last week to build a model of asset pricing that can explain 5 facts that have puzzled the literature at one time or another.
Facts Standard deviation of price dividend ratio is very high (about 1/2 the mean of the PD ratio) First-order quarterly autocorrelation of PD ratio is vary high Standard deviation of stock returns is almost 4 times as large as standard deviation of dividend growth PD ratio is good long run predictor of stock returns Equity premium puzzle: return on risky stocks is too high relative to bonds for standard models  Model There is a unit mass of infinitely lived investors, endowed with one unit of a stock that can be traded in a competitive market and that pays a per period dividend D in units of a perishable consumption good.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Baley:2016wr (Firm uncertainty cycles and the propagation of nominal shocks)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/10/25/baley2016wr-firm-uncertainty-cycles-and-the-propagation-of-nominal-shocks/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/10/25/baley2016wr-firm-uncertainty-cycles-and-the-propagation-of-nominal-shocks/</guid>
      <description>This paper develops a model with menu costs for adjusting prices and imperfect information about idiosyncratic productivity shocks. They conduct monetary policy experiments and conclude that the distribution of firm level uncertainty is important for the propagation of monetary shocks.
Model In this model time is continuous. There is a representative consumer, a continuum of monopolistically competitive firms, and a monetary authority.
In the baseline model, the monetary authority keeps the money supply fixed at its initial level.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ikegami:2016ek (Poverty Traps and the Social Protection Paradox)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/10/18/ikegami2016ek-poverty-traps-and-the-social-protection-paradox/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/10/18/ikegami2016ek-poverty-traps-and-the-social-protection-paradox/</guid>
      <description>This paper presents and analyzes a stylized model of poverty traps in developing economies.
Baseline model In the baseline model there are a finite number of agents.
Agent’s are characterized by a constant level of innate ability α and an evolving stock of capital k.
Each period, agents choose which of two DRS production technologies they wish to operate in that period. Switching technologies is costless. Both technologies have innate ability multiplied by physical capital raised to a power less than one.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kaplan:2016fe (Non-durable Consumption and Housing Net Worth in the Great Recession: Evidence from Easily Accessible Data.)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/10/11/kaplan2016fe-non-durable-consumption-and-housing-net-worth-in-the-great-recession-evidence-from-easily-accessible-data./</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/10/11/kaplan2016fe-non-durable-consumption-and-housing-net-worth-in-the-great-recession-evidence-from-easily-accessible-data./</guid>
      <description>In 2013; Mian, Rao, Sufi used proprietary data on the US housing market (obtained from Core Logic) and personal consumption expenditures (obtained from master card) from 2006-2009 to estimate that the elasticity of consumption expenditures to changes in the housing share of household net worth.
This paper replicates the main results from Mian, Rao, and Sufi using data that is more easily accessed by economists in academia.
Data The authors proxy the housing data from Core Logic, using housing data from Zillow.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Amiti:2014ez (Importers, Exporters, and Exchange Rate Disconnect.)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/10/04/amiti2014ez-importers-exporters-and-exchange-rate-disconnect./</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/10/04/amiti2014ez-importers-exporters-and-exchange-rate-disconnect./</guid>
      <description>This paper aims to explain the low exchange rate pass-through for exporters. Exchange rate pass-through is the response in export prices to movement in the exchange rate.
Model The theoretical model is not the focus of the authors’ analysis in this paper. They write down a fairly complicated model, derive some of the equilibrium conditions, then use the implications of the equilibrium conditions as testable predictions they take to the data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kee:2016ej (Trade adjustment dynamics and the welfare gains from trade)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/09/27/kee2016ej-trade-adjustment-dynamics-and-the-welfare-gains-from-trade/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/09/27/kee2016ej-trade-adjustment-dynamics-and-the-welfare-gains-from-trade/</guid>
      <description>A mostly empirical paper that examines the inputs used by Chinese firms to produce exported goods.
DVAR The empirical analysis in this paper is centered around a variable named DVA, which stands for domestic value added in exports.
To derive DVA, we start with total revenue. The authors break total revenue into the sum of
 profits labor costs capital costs materials from domestic sources materials from foreign sources  Because intermediate good producers can get their inputs from China or foreign sources, the domestic and foreign materials sources are decomposed into Chinese and non-Chinese components.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Brumm, Mikushin, Scheidegger and Schenk (2015) (Scalable high-dimensional dynamic stochastic economic modeling)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/05/09/brumm-mikushin-scheidegger-and-schenk-2015-scalable-high-dimensional-dynamic-stochastic-economic-modeling/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/05/09/brumm-mikushin-scheidegger-and-schenk-2015-scalable-high-dimensional-dynamic-stochastic-economic-modeling/</guid>
      <description>An economist, a physicist, and two computer scientists walk into a bar…
This is a computational paper that describes and algorithm featuring an adaptive sparse grid and discuss implementation details on a sophisticated HPC cluster.
Model They provide examples of their algorithm and computation using a standard international real business cycle model. This is not the interesting part of the paper, so I will not focus on it here.
Computation Adaptive Sparse Grids The first main contribution of this paper is to introduce economists to a specialized flavor of function approximation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Farias Saure Weintraub (2012) (An approximate dynamic programming approach to solving dynamic oligopoly models)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/05/03/farias-saure-weintraub-2012-an-approximate-dynamic-programming-approach-to-solving-dynamic-oligopoly-models/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/05/03/farias-saure-weintraub-2012-an-approximate-dynamic-programming-approach-to-solving-dynamic-oligopoly-models/</guid>
      <description>This paper builds on the approximate linear programming work of Farias and van Roy that I presented a few weeks ago and applies a version of that technique to a dynamic oligopoly model.
The actual model is not novel to this research, so I will spend most of my time talking about the algorithm.
Model  The model is set in discrete time and multiple firms compete in a single good market over an infinite horizon.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Timoshenko (2015) (Learning versus sunk costs explanations of export persistence)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/04/26/timoshenko-2015-learning-versus-sunk-costs-explanations-of-export-persistence/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/04/26/timoshenko-2015-learning-versus-sunk-costs-explanations-of-export-persistence/</guid>
      <description>This is a mostly empirical paper that tries to decompose exporter persistence into sunk cost and learning components.
Model Let firms be indexed by i. Firms have two state variables: productivity zi, t that follows an AR(1) process and export experience Ai, t. In Ai, t is the number of consecutive periods a firm has exported coming into period t.
Without microfoudations, Timoshenko assumes that per-period sales are the Melitz result, multiplied by a function g of export experience:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Timoshenko (2015) (Product switching in a model of learning)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/04/26/timoshenko-2015-product-switching-in-a-model-of-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/04/26/timoshenko-2015-product-switching-in-a-model-of-learning/</guid>
      <description>This paper documents facts about Brazilian manufacturing firms that switch their bundle of exported products over time. The author then builds a Melitz-style trade model that attempts to explain these facts.
Empirics The author uses data product level data on Brazilian manufacturing firms to document several stylized facts.
 72% of continuing exporters alter their product mix every year (add new exported products or drop existing exported products) 83% of all Brazilian exports come from these product switching firms The proportion of exporters who do product switching falls with age in export market The frequency with which exporters engage in product switching falls with age The exit rate of product switching firms is lower than aggregate exit rate for all ages of exporter.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Konda and Tsitsiklis (2003) (Actor-critic Algorithms)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/04/19/konda-and-tsitsiklis-2003-actor-critic-algorithms/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/04/19/konda-and-tsitsiklis-2003-actor-critic-algorithms/</guid>
      <description>Background When a Markov decision process (MDP) is formulated as a dynamic programming problem, the reinforcement learning literature proposes are two classic classes of algorithms to solve them. Let’s briefly review these types of algorithms and point out strengths and weaknesses of each.
1: Actor only methods We can think of an actor as a fictitious character that operates on a policy rule.
When I talk about the performance of an actor, I mean the value of following a policy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Busoniu, DeSchutter, Babuska(2010) (Approximate dynamic programming and reinforcement learning)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/04/12/busoniu-deschutter-babuska2010-approximate-dynamic-programming-and-reinforcement-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/04/12/busoniu-deschutter-babuska2010-approximate-dynamic-programming-and-reinforcement-learning/</guid>
      <description>This paper provides an overview of various solution concepts that belong to the families of approximate dynamic programming and reinforcement learning.
I will discuss an alternative representation of a dynamic programming that is often used in this literature and provide an overview of some solution methods that are common with this representation.
Basics: Q-functions In economics, the standard representation of a dynamic programming problem is to define a recursive function V that maps from a state space into the real line.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>de Farias &amp; van Roy (2003) (The Linear Programming Approach to Approximate Dynamic Programming)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/03/29/de-farias--van-roy-2003-the-linear-programming-approach-to-approximate-dynamic-programming/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/03/29/de-farias--van-roy-2003-the-linear-programming-approach-to-approximate-dynamic-programming/</guid>
      <description>This paper was published in Operations Research and as such they use a different notation and jargon than economists. I’ll present some of their main results, but in a language and notation that is familiar to me.
Background Consider a typical dynamic programming problem faced by an economic agent, which we summarize by the following Bellman equation:

$$V(x) = \underset{c \in \Gamma(x)}{\max} u(x, c) + \beta E V(x&#39;)$$
Now define the natural operator associated with the Bellman, which we call T:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hull (2015) (Approximate dynamic programming with post-decision states as a solution method for dynamic economic models)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/03/22/hull-2015-approximate-dynamic-programming-with-post-decision-states-as-a-solution-method-for-dynamic-economic-models/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/03/22/hull-2015-approximate-dynamic-programming-with-post-decision-states-as-a-solution-method-for-dynamic-economic-models/</guid>
      <description>This paper presents a stochastic simulation method for solving dynamic economic models.
The ideas in this paper lean on a literature sometimes known as approximate dynamic programming and can enable us to solve models with many state variables and non-convexities in objectives and constraints.
My intent is to summarize the core theoretical ideas behind the algorithm.
Main idea: Post decision states Notation: classic Bellman equation Consider a stationary economic model where at time t the state is summarized by a vector st of endogenous state variables and a vector xt of exogenous state variables.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Achdou, Han, Lasry, Lions, Moll (2015) (Hetergenous agent models in continuous time)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/03/08/achdou-han-lasry-lions-moll-2015-hetergenous-agent-models-in-continuous-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/03/08/achdou-han-lasry-lions-moll-2015-hetergenous-agent-models-in-continuous-time/</guid>
      <description>This paper looks at the class of equations used to represent and solve heterogenous agent models in continuous time and presents a solution approach that is efficient and tractable.
Model A few models were presented in the paper. Here we’ll take the simplest one: a continuous time version of the Huggett economy.
In this economy there are a continuum of individuals that are heterogeneous in their wealth and income.
Individuals value streams of consumption using CRRA preferences and a constant discount factor ρ.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Costinot, Rodriguez, Werning (2016) (Micro to Macro: Optimal Trade Policy with Firm Heterogeneity)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/03/01/costinot-rodriguez-werning-2016-micro-to-macro-optimal-trade-policy-with-firm-heterogeneity/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/03/01/costinot-rodriguez-werning-2016-micro-to-macro-optimal-trade-policy-with-firm-heterogeneity/</guid>
      <description>This paper extends the Meltiz framework to allow for optimal tariff policies.
Model This model extends a two country Melitz framework in two ways:
Allows for heterogeneity in variable and fixed costs. This will be a policy instrument where governments can set firm specific tariffs The representative consumer in each country has a constant elasticity of substitution across all varieties procued within a country, but that elasticity can differ across countries.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Eaton, Eslava, Jinkins, Krizan, Tybout (2014) (A search and learning model of export dynamics)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/02/16/eaton-eslava-jinkins-krizan-tybout-2014-a-search-and-learning-model-of-export-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/02/16/eaton-eslava-jinkins-krizan-tybout-2014-a-search-and-learning-model-of-export-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>Overview A primarily empirical paper that studies how allowing exporting firms to learn about demand for their product impacts firm dynamics in a Melitz style trade model.
Data and stylized facts Let’s start with the data.
The data set used in this paper describes all imports by US buyers from Colombian exporters from 1992-2009. The source is the U.S. Census Bureau’s Longitudinal Foreign Trade Transactions Database (LFTTD).
Using this data, the authors report the following stylized facts:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Niepmann (2013) (Banking across borders)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/02/16/niepmann-2013-banking-across-borders/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/02/16/niepmann-2013-banking-across-borders/</guid>
      <description>Intro This introduces heterogenous banks into a general equilibrium trade model in the flavor of Melitz. There are also empirical exercises that show that the model can generate some features of German banking data.
Model We will describe the model in two stages:
Closed economy, where we will characterize economic setting and the optimization problem of each agent. Open economy, where combine 2 closed economies and allow them to trade  Closed economy The economy consists of the following agents:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Das, Roberts, Tybout (2007) (Market entry costs, producer heterogeneity, and export dynamics)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/02/09/das-roberts-tybout-2007-market-entry-costs-producer-heterogeneity-and-export-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/02/09/das-roberts-tybout-2007-market-entry-costs-producer-heterogeneity-and-export-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>Intro This paper takes an empirical look at a variant of the Melitz model from last week.
Model  Assumptions:
Domestic and foreign product markets are monopolistically competitive and segmented. In Melitz we got segmentation from CRS production. Marginal costs do not respond to output shocks: domestic shocks do not impact optimal export levels Firms are heterogeneous in marginal production costs and foreign demand functions (so profits differ) Future exchange rate, production costs, and foreign demand shifters are unkown, but Markov Firms must pay an up-front cost to enter export market in addition to per period fixed operating costs   For a firm already in the export market, export profits are characterized by log-linear (Cobb Douglass in levels) function of firm-specific characteristics, the real exchange rate, and a random disturbance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Melitz 2003 (The impact of trade on intra-industry reallocations and aggregate industry productivity)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/02/02/melitz-2003-the-impact-of-trade-on-intra-industry-reallocations-and-aggregate-industry-productivity/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/02/02/melitz-2003-the-impact-of-trade-on-intra-industry-reallocations-and-aggregate-industry-productivity/</guid>
      <description>Intro An early paper that introduced a now common framework for thinking about firm entry, export decision, and exit in trade models.
Model I’ll describe the model in two stages:
A closed economy version of the model with a single country An open economy version with many similar countries  Closed economy Consumers There is a representative consumer with CES a utility function over a continuum of goods. The elasticity of substitution between any two goods is σ &amp;gt; 1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kehoe2015 (Discount Rates , Learning by Doing and Employment Fluctuations)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2015/12/08/kehoe2015-discount-rates--learning-by-doing-and-employment-fluctuations/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2015/12/08/kehoe2015-discount-rates--learning-by-doing-and-employment-fluctuations/</guid>
      <description>Model The model is a search and matching model in the flavor of DPM, with a few modifications.
Consumers There are a continuum of identical consumers that have the following characteristics:
 They face both idiosyncratic and aggregate risk (both productivity shocks that are AR(1) in logs) Have a constant hazard probability ϕ of dying each period Are organized into families that pool all idiosyncratic risk and exhibit perfect idiosyncratic risk sharing within the family  The family problem:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Betts2008 (Real exchange rate movements and the relative price of non-traded goods)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2015/11/24/betts2008-real-exchange-rate-movements-and-the-relative-price-of-non-traded-goods/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2015/11/24/betts2008-real-exchange-rate-movements-and-the-relative-price-of-non-traded-goods/</guid>
      <description>Outline An empirical paper that examines the relationship between the real exchange rate and the relative price of non-traded vs traded goods.
Modes of thought At the time of writing the paper, there were two main modes of thought for thinking about real exchange rate movements
 Traditional view: all movements in bilateral real exchange rate between two countries are due to fluctuations in the bilateral relative price of non-traded to traded goods.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ruhl2015 (New Exporter Dynamics)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2015/11/17/ruhl2015-new-exporter-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2015/11/17/ruhl2015-new-exporter-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>Intro The authors did some empirical work with data on Columbian firms to arrive at two stlyized facts about new exporters (firms who recently began exporting):
On average, entrant exporters are smaller than long-time exporters The probability of exiting the export market falls with tenure  The goal of the paper is to write a model that can match the data on these two dimensions.
Model Partial equilibrium version of the model I presented last week.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alessandria2014 (Trade adjustment dynamics and the welfare gains from trade)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2015/11/10/alessandria2014-trade-adjustment-dynamics-and-the-welfare-gains-from-trade/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2015/11/10/alessandria2014-trade-adjustment-dynamics-and-the-welfare-gains-from-trade/</guid>
      <description>Model This is a general equilibrium trade model that focuses on producer export, entry, expansion, and exit. The structure of the model nests other standard models such as Krugman, Melitz and others.
In the model there are two symmetric countries. Within each country there are consumers, final goods producers, intermediate goods producers, and a government.
Consumers  A unit mass of identical consumers live in each country and inelastically supple one unit of labor Choose sequences of capital, risk free one period bond holdings, and consumption to maximize expected present discounted value of CRRA utility over consumption.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Jermann2012 (Macroeconomic Effects of Financial Shocks)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2015/11/03/jermann2012-macroeconomic-effects-of-financial-shocks/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2015/11/03/jermann2012-macroeconomic-effects-of-financial-shocks/</guid>
      <description>Model Firm Problem The model has a representative firm that uses capital and labor within CRS Cobb Douglas production technology, subject to TFP shock.
Capital evolution is standard: kt + 1 = (1 − δ)kt + it
Firms also raise resources through debt and equity financing:
 Debt financing comes through the issuance of a non-state contingent one period bond.  Debt financing has a tax advantage relative to equity (Rt = 1 + rt(1 − τ))  Equity financing comes through dividend payments (or receipts) from shareholders  Total cost to firms of dividend payouts is the payment amount plus a quadratic term in deviation of payout from target (steady state).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Iskhakov2013 (Recursive Lexicographical Search: Finding all Markov Perfect Equilibria of Finite State Directional Dynamic Games)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2015/10/27/iskhakov2013-recursive-lexicographical-search-finding-all-markov-perfect-equilibria-of-finite-state-directional-dynamic-games/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2015/10/27/iskhakov2013-recursive-lexicographical-search-finding-all-markov-perfect-equilibria-of-finite-state-directional-dynamic-games/</guid>
      <description>Outline The authors of this paper do 3 main things:
Describe a particular class of Dynamic economic games Describe two algorithms for computing Markov perfect equilibria of those games Give two detailed, non-trivial examples of how to apply the algorithms to games in this class  We won’t have time to touch on the examples, but my goal today is to describe the class of models and explain the key components of the algorithms.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chassang2010 (Building routines: Learning, cooperation, and the dynamics of incomplete relational contracts)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2015/10/20/chassang2010-building-routines-learning-cooperation-and-the-dynamics-of-incomplete-relational-contracts/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2015/10/20/chassang2010-building-routines-learning-cooperation-and-the-dynamics-of-incomplete-relational-contracts/</guid>
      <description>Model Mechanics Two agents, infinite horizon, discrete time, and each agent has a common discount factor δ.
Each period agent 1 can choose to enter or exit.
Player 2 has a countably finite set of actions, represented as the set 𝒜, which is equal to the natural numbers. Each period an i.i.d subset of A ⊂ 𝒜 is drawn. This is both the state of the economy in each period and agent 2’s feasible actions set for the period.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Borovicka2011b (Risk Price Dynamics)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2015/10/13/borovicka2011b-risk-price-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2015/10/13/borovicka2011b-risk-price-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>Intro Goal: Characterize the main conceptual composition of risk and shock elasticities and provide an example of their interpretation in a macro model.
Outline:
 General continuous time framework  Stochastic process for state Growth processes and cash flows Perturbations Elasticities  Simple example  Do the BL model. Can talk about choosing αd = ei for i = 1, 2, 3.   Mathematical Framework I will briefly explain the mathematical framework used in this and related papers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Angeletos, Iovino, La&#39;O (2015) (Real Rigidity , Nominal Rigidity , and the Social Value of Information)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2015/10/06/angeletos-iovino-lao-2015-real-rigidity--nominal-rigidity--and-the-social-value-of-information/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2015/10/06/angeletos-iovino-lao-2015-real-rigidity--nominal-rigidity--and-the-social-value-of-information/</guid>
      <description>Model The model in this paper is fairly simple. The interesting analysis in this paper has to do with the information structure
Setup Agents in the model either live in the mainland or on one of a continuum of islands
Each island:
 Is populated by a continuum of workers and a continuum of monopolistic firms. Within each island all firms are identical, as are workers Firms:  Hire workers through competitive labor markets Use labor in a linear production technology: product of labor supply island specific TFP  The log of TFP in each period is the sum of an aggregate and an idiosyncratic shock All shocks in the model are mean zero Gaussians, unless otherwise specified.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Schorfheide, Song, &amp; Yaron (2014) (Identifying Long-Run Risks: A Bayesian Mixed-Frequency Approach (@Schorfheide2014))</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2015/09/15/schorfheide-song--yaron-2014-identifying-long-run-risks-a-bayesian-mixed-frequency-approach-schorfheide2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2015/09/15/schorfheide-song--yaron-2014-identifying-long-run-risks-a-bayesian-mixed-frequency-approach-schorfheide2014/</guid>
      <description>Outline This is paper is more empirical than theoretical.
Theoretical contributions are to specify more flexible stochastic environment than in other long run risk models a la Bansal et al. (2007)
Empirical contributions are
 form a linear approximation of the stochastic environment to apply state space methods within an MCMC algorithm Show how to incorporate data of various frequencies and accuracy in the inference algorithm  Overview of this talk:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>He &amp; Krishnamurthy (2013) (Intermediary Asset Pricing)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2015/09/07/he--krishnamurthy-2013-intermediary-asset-pricing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2015/09/07/he--krishnamurthy-2013-intermediary-asset-pricing/</guid>
      <description>Model This is two-type agent, continuous time model of financial intermediaries. He and Krishnamurthy (2013)
Agents are either households or specialists.
Distinction will be made clear once we understand the market structure
Market structure  One risk-free short run bond in zero net supply  All agents can freely buy this asset Specialists can also short  One risky asset whose dividends evolve as GBM  Only specialists can purchase this asset, however they can do so in behalf of households via an intermediary mechanism to be explained shortly Net supply normalized to 1   Technology (how markets work) Each period between t and t + dt is split into 5 mini-periods:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>Section 1 (intro):  Two channels:  productivity channel says move from low productivity to high productivity country risk-sharing channel says move from low marginal utility (MU) to high MU country  Section 2 (lit review):  Differ from Tretvol on three dimensions: (1) look at long run shocks, (2) Tretvoll considers standard BKK capital accumulation (TODO: what is used here) (3) parameter values are closer to asset pricing than RBC literature (RRA = 10, IES &amp;gt; 1 where tretvoll has RRA=100, IES &amp;lt; 1)  Section 3 (empirics):  Used data on G7 countries to show three main results: Positive short run productivity news leads to net inflow of capital Positive long run productivity news leads to net outflow of captial Did estimation for US vs UK and then for US vs all other G6.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>