<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sargent Reading Group Notes</title>
    <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Sargent Reading Group Notes</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-EN</language>
    <managingEditor>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</webMaster>
    <copyright>(c) 2015 Spencer Lyon.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://srg.spencerlyon.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Kee:2016ej (Trade adjustment dynamics and the welfare gains from trade)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/09/27/kee2016ej-trade-adjustment-dynamics-and-the-welfare-gains-from-trade/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/09/27/kee2016ej-trade-adjustment-dynamics-and-the-welfare-gains-from-trade/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A mostly empirical paper that examines the inputs used by Chinese firms to produce exported goods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;dvar&#34;&gt;DVAR&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The empirical analysis in this paper is centered around a variable named DVA, which stands for domestic value added in exports.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To derive DVA, we start with total revenue. The authors break total revenue into the sum of&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;profits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;labor costs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;capital costs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;materials from domestic sources&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;materials from foreign sources&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because intermediate good producers can get their inputs from China or foreign sources, the domestic and foreign materials sources are decomposed into Chinese and non-Chinese components.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DVA is then defined as the sum of&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;profits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;labor costs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;capital costs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chinese component of materials from domestic sources&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chinese component of materials from foreign sources&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors restrict their analysis to processing exporters, which means exporters who do not sell any of their final good in domestic markets. With this restriction the value of total exports is equal to total revenue. In this case DVA can be written as total exports less cost of imported materials plus and adjustment to account for foreign content materials from domestic materials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the form of DVA that is used throughout the paper. The important takeaway is that DAV is increasing in total exports and decreasing in cost of imported materials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;data&#34;&gt;Data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors use Chinese customs data that includes all exporting firms from 2000-2007. They apply three criterion to narrow down this universe to the final data set used in their analyses:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Look at only processing firms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Look at firms that operate in a single industry (difficult to decompose share of imports and exports within a firm across industries)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Look at firms that aren&amp;rsquo;t &amp;quot;too extreme&amp;quot; in their importing and exporting behavior (an extreme exporter is a firm that imports strictly more than it exports &amp;ndash; selling the additional imported goods to other domestic producers)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In all analyses they normalize DVA by total exports for each firm. The resulting variable is named DVAR.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;main-findings&#34;&gt;Main findings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll talk about 3 main findings:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Aggregate DVAR increased from near 45% to 55% from 2000 to 2007. This finding is also robust across industries, where 15 reported industries showed a similar evolution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The increase in DVAR is driven by firms actively substituting imported materials for domestic materials, not by rising domestic production costs (e.g. labor and capital costs). This has policy implications. They do some regressions that show that changes in import tariffs for domestic, non-processing firms &amp;ndash; firms who sell input goods to the firms in our sample &amp;ndash; and rising FDI liberalization made significant contributions to rising DVAR.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Restricting the analysis to processing exporters is not a bad estimate of total behavior. Recent work has used input-output tables to document facts about aggregate DVAR movement. The numbers reported here (using transactions level data, but only for processing firms) accounts for almost all the aggregate change.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Brumm, Mikushin, Scheidegger and Schenk (2015) (Scalable high-dimensional dynamic stochastic economic modeling)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/05/09/brumm-mikushin-scheidegger-and-schenk-2015-scalable-high-dimensional-dynamic-stochastic-economic-modeling/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/05/09/brumm-mikushin-scheidegger-and-schenk-2015-scalable-high-dimensional-dynamic-stochastic-economic-modeling/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;An economist, a physicist, and two computer scientists walk into a bar...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a computational paper that describes and algorithm featuring an adaptive sparse grid and discuss implementation details on a sophisticated HPC cluster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;model&#34;&gt;Model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They provide examples of their algorithm and computation using a standard international real business cycle model. This is not the interesting part of the paper, so I will not focus on it here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;computation&#34;&gt;Computation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;adaptive-sparse-grids&#34;&gt;Adaptive Sparse Grids&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first main contribution of this paper is to introduce economists to a specialized flavor of function approximation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors use familiar linear Splines; but do so on a sparse, adaptive, and hierarchical grid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By sparse I mean that the n-dimensional grid is not composed of the tensor product, or Cartesian product, of all univariate grids. This helps alleviate the curse of dimensionality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By adaptive I mean that the knot vector for the grid in each dimension will change as the solution algorithm for the economic problem proceeds. This helps preserve accuracy of function approximation routines when the grid is sparse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By hierarchical I mean that the grid for a particular level of refinement is a strict subset of the grid for all higher levels of refinement. This helps reduce computation costs as the basis functions for higher order terms only require a few additional function evaluations instead of a full basis matrix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;algorithm&#34;&gt;Algorithm&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second main contribution of the paper is an algorithm that leverages this special interpolation scheme to solve high dimensional dynamic stochastic models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main steps of the iterative portion of the algorithm are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start with the coarsest refinement level &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;l&lt;/em&gt; = 1&lt;/span&gt; for all dimensions. Call the grid G. Choose a maximum refinement level&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Also Initialize &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;G&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;o&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;l&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;d&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;G&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;w&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; to be the empty set&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;While G and &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;G&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;o&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;l&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;d&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; are not the same (NOTE: at end of this loop explain the while goes until we are at Lmax or until we don&#39;t add refinement points)
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For each grid point in &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;G&lt;/em&gt; \ &lt;em&gt;G&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;o&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;l&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;d&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Solve the system of non-linear equations characterizing the optimal controls at that grid point (note you will need to interpolate over the current guess of the policy function) to obtain a new guess for the policy rule at that point&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the distance between the old and new guess for the policy at the grid point is greater than some threshold, add the neighboring points at the next refinement level to G_new&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;G&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;o&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;l&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;d&lt;/em&gt; = &lt;em&gt;G&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;G&lt;/em&gt; = &lt;em&gt;G&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;o&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;l&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;d&lt;/em&gt; ∪ &lt;em&gt;G&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;w&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;G&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;w&lt;/em&gt; = ∅&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;l&lt;/em&gt; + =1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Calculate the error for this iteration as the sup norm over the implied policy rule from the current iteration and the previous iteration&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notice that this algorithm will start with very few points across the entire domain and iteratively add points only in regions where the policy rule has dramatic changes. This will naturally cause the grid to adapt and add more grid points in areas of the state space that feature non-linearities or discontinuities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This algorithm was implemented by coders who know their stuff! They build on cutting edge software and run their code on state of the art super computers in Switzerland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results are impressive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On just one node of the super-computer, they were able to achieve a 30x speedup for their code by utilizing a GPU and multi-threaded parallelism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They were then able to scale that code from a single node to up to 2048 nodes to achieve a speedup on the order of 10,000x.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They compare their algorithm to a non-adaptive sparse grid and find that the log 10 average Euler errors from their algorithm are smaller on average than the sparse grid case, but run time is up 2 to 3 orders of magnitude smaller.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Farias Saure Weintraub (2012) (An approximate dynamic programming approach to solving dynamic oligopoly models)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/05/03/farias-saure-weintraub-2012-an-approximate-dynamic-programming-approach-to-solving-dynamic-oligopoly-models/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/05/03/farias-saure-weintraub-2012-an-approximate-dynamic-programming-approach-to-solving-dynamic-oligopoly-models/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This paper builds on the approximate linear programming work of Farias and van Roy that I presented a few weeks ago and applies a version of that technique to a dynamic oligopoly model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The actual model is not novel to this research, so I will spend most of my time talking about the algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;model&#34;&gt;Model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The model is set in discrete time and multiple firms compete in a single good market over an infinite horizon.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Firms are identified by a firm specific state x that takes on an integer value between 0 and some upper limit xbar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The aggregate state s is a histogram of the number of firms at each individual state (a vector of xbar+1 integers)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The maximum number of incumbent firms is fixed at N. Each period there are &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;N&lt;/em&gt; − &lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;u&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt;(&lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; possible entrants. Entrants do not produce or earn profits in the first period.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Incumbents choose an investment level that determines the probability of remaining in the same state, or moving up or down one step to a neighboring state in the next period.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Each period the following events occur in this order:
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Incumbent firms draw a random sell-off cost and decide if they want to exit. If they stay, they make investment decisions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Each potential entrant draws a random entry cost and makes entry decision&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Incumbent firms compete in spot market and receive prices&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Exiting firms exit and receive sell off values&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shocks are realized, each firm that stays transitions to a new state.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The equilibrium concept studied in this paper is a symmetric Markov perfect equilibrium. In this context a MPE is an investment/exit strategy for incumbents and an entry strategy for potential entrants such that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;given that all other incumbents follow the exit/investment strategy, each incumbent does not want to deviate from that strategy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For all states with a positive number of entrants, the cutoff entry value is equal to the expected discounted value of profits of entering the industry&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;computation&#34;&gt;Computation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;naive-algorithm&#34;&gt;Naive algorithm&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To understand the contribution of this paper, it is helpful to have a basic understanding of a naive &amp;quot;brute force&amp;quot; algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The naive algorithm presented here is iterating on a best response operator and proceeds as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choose some initial investment, exit, and entry policy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Repeat the following until the policies are close enough:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Taking that N-1 players use the current guess for the policy, compute a best response for one agent. To do this you can apply standard dynamic programming algorithms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compute some notion of a norm between the best response and the current guess for the policy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set the current guess equal to the best response and continue if needed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This algorithm is robust, but has one major drawback: the curse of dimensionality. For in a model with 20 incumbents and 20 individual states, there are over a thousand billion states that must be iterated over when computing the best response.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;approximate-dynamic-programming-algorithm&#34;&gt;Approximate dynamic programming algorithm&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors of this paper make 4 modifications to the naive algorithm:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They form the linear program version of the dynamic programming problem to solve for the best response&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They apply approximate linear programming approach of de Farias and van Roy to reduce the number of variables the solver must find&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They use constraint sampling to only enforce a subset of the constraints of the linear program&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They choose basis functions that are especially well suited to their problem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors do a few numerical experiments. The experiments all revolve around solving for the MPE exactly or approximately and then computing implied long run aggregates, such as average producer and consumer surplus, average share of ith largest firm, and average investment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;exercise-1-small-model-exact-comparison&#34;&gt;Exercise 1: small model, exact comparison&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a relatively small version of the model (number of incumbents low), they are able to apply the naive algorithm and compute the true MPE. They also solve the model using their proposed algorithm and show that the aggregates are always within 8% of the true values, typically within 2%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Runtime for their algorithm is on the order of minutes in each case. With a max of 3 incumbents, runtime for the naive algorithm is on the order of seconds. When the max number of incumbents is 5, the naive algorithm takes a few hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;exercise-2-large-model-compare-oe&#34;&gt;Exercise 2: large model, compare OE&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They also run a similar experiment for a much larger model where they compare a current state of the art algorithm to their proposed algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They find that the aggregates are always within 13% of one another, but often within 5%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the state of the art is also an approximation, this doesn&#39;t say much more than that both algorithms appear to approximate a similar thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They comment that the runtime for a version of the model with 20 incumbents is a couple of hours. Unfortunately they don&#39;t elaborate on the difference in runtime between the algorithms.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Timoshenko (2015) (Learning versus sunk costs explanations of export persistence)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/04/26/timoshenko-2015-learning-versus-sunk-costs-explanations-of-export-persistence/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/04/26/timoshenko-2015-learning-versus-sunk-costs-explanations-of-export-persistence/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is a &lt;em&gt;mostly&lt;/em&gt; empirical paper that tries to decompose exporter persistence into sunk cost and learning components.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;model&#34;&gt;Model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let firms be indexed by &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;. Firms have two state variables: productivity &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;z&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; that follows an AR(1) process and export experience &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;A&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt;. In &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;A&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; is the number of consecutive periods a firm has exported coming into period &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without microfoudations, Timoshenko assumes that per-period sales are the Melitz result, multiplied by a function &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;g&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; of export experience:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;$S(z, A) = g(A) E P^{\sigma-1} \left( \frac{\sigma}{\sigma-1} \frac{\tau w}{\exp(z)} \right)^{1-\sigma}$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a firm chooses to export, profits are given by &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;π&lt;/em&gt;(&lt;em&gt;z&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;A&lt;/em&gt;)=&lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;(&lt;em&gt;z&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;A&lt;/em&gt;)/&lt;em&gt;σ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; less a sunk market-entry cost if &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;A&lt;/em&gt; = 0&lt;/span&gt;. If a firm does not export, period profits are 0.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Timoshenko assumes that &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;g&lt;/em&gt;(&lt;em&gt;A&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; is increasing in &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;A&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;. She calls this the age-dependence (or learning) assumption and uses it to get empirical results later on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Export decision problem has a policy rule characterized by a pair of cutoff productivities &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;z&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;h&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; &amp;gt; &lt;em&gt;z&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;l&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt;: a exit threshold &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;z&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;l&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;(&lt;em&gt;A&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; and an entry threshold &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;z&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;h&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt;. Firms enter when they get a productivity draw above &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;z&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;h&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt;. They continue to export until productivity falls below &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;z&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;l&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;(&lt;em&gt;A&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;z&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;l&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;(&lt;em&gt;A&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; is a function of &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;A&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; because there is a hysteresis effect caused by &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;$\frac{\partial g(A)}{\partial A} &amp;gt; 0$&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;z&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;h&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; is not a function of &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;A&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, because by definition of &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;A&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; we have &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;A&lt;/em&gt; = 0&lt;/span&gt; for all firms considering entry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;empirics&#34;&gt;Empirics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Timoshenko then does some empirical work to try to tease out the importance of the &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;g&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; function on export sales and participation. Because there are sunk export costs in the model, she claims that considering both &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;g&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; and sunk costs isolates all learning effects into coefficients for &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;g&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To do this she starts from her reduced form theoretical model to build an empirical model. She controls for firm characteristics like location, domestic sales, investment, labor and materials expenditures, capital stock, wage rate, productivity, etc. She also builds in plant specific random effects. The result is an system of estimable equations that effectively regress the export decision rule on firm characteristics, exporter age dummies, and other controls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;aside&#34;&gt;Aside&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t necessarily agree with her main claim. Without micro-foundations, &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;g&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; doesn&amp;rsquo;t say anything about learning specifically. As it is written &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;g&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; is a simply a mechanism that causes sales and profits to increase with exporter age. This could be learning, more efficient production, more efficient transporting of goods, exogenous rise in foreign demand, market penetration/firm reputation in foreign market, etc. You might make an argument that the efficiency angles are a subset of learning: firms are &lt;em&gt;learning&lt;/em&gt; to be more efficient, but I believe separating different channels of learning is important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using plant level data on Columbian firms in the 1980&amp;rsquo;s Timoshenko finds evidence that supports her age-dependence hypothesis. The findings are robust across industries. The punchline is that about &amp;frac12; of the value of the state dependence parameter is attributed to sunk costs and about &amp;frac12; is attributed to age-dependence. By state dependence I mean the impact of yesterday&amp;rsquo;s export status on today&amp;rsquo;s export decision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;refs&#34; class=&#34;references&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Timoshenko (2015) (Product switching in a model of learning)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/04/26/timoshenko-2015-product-switching-in-a-model-of-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/04/26/timoshenko-2015-product-switching-in-a-model-of-learning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This paper documents facts about Brazilian manufacturing firms that switch their bundle of exported products over time. The author then builds a Melitz-style trade model that attempts to explain these facts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;empirics&#34;&gt;Empirics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The author uses data product level data on Brazilian manufacturing firms to document several stylized facts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;72% of continuing exporters alter their product mix every year (add new exported products or drop existing exported products)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;83% of all Brazilian exports come from these product switching firms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The proportion of exporters who do product switching falls with age in export market&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The frequency with which exporters engage in product switching falls with age&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The exit rate of product switching firms is lower than aggregate exit rate for all ages of exporter.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Conditional on an exporter adding new products, over 1/2 of exporter products are added products&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;model&#34;&gt;Model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The model in this paper extends Melitz (2003) in two ways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consumers have firm specific demand shocks in their consumption aggregator&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Firms of a particular brand produce a finite, discrete number of products&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s the main points of the model:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;consumers&#34;&gt;Consumers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In each of &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;N&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; countries, there is a representative consumer that has log preferences over an aggregate consumption good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aggregate good is a CES aggregated bundle of firm goods from all &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;N&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; countries. Each firm good is hit with a time-varying, firm-and-import-country-specific demand shock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The firm goods are a CES aggregation of a finite number of differentiated products produced by the firm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consumers inelastically supply a country specific fixed labor each period and earn labor income from firms. They also own firms in their country and retain all profits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consumers take prices and wages as given maximize the utility of consuming the aggregate good subject to total expenditures being equal to labor income plus firm profits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The output of the consumer problem is a demand function for each product from each firm in each country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This demand function is a function of the consumer&#39;s income, the current demand shock for the firm and prices. Crucially, it can be inverted to give prices as a function of quantity and the demand shock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;firms&#34;&gt;Firms&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firm&#39;s differ in their ability &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;φ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; to produce all their products. This ability or productivity is constant over time and across products and is drawn from a Pareto distribution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The demand shock in the consumer&#39;s CES aggregator is the sum of a constant firm specific component and a mean zero normally distributed iid shock drawn each period. The firm specific constant component is drawn from a normal distribution with known (to the firm) mean and variance. The prior beliefs of every firm are that the firm specific demand shock is drawn from its true distribution. Because signals and priors are normal, posterior beliefs are also normal and sufficient statistics are the mean and variance of the firm specific component.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firms choose the quantity of each product to be sold in each country, &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; seeing the value of the demand shock for their firm in a given period. Consumers&#39; see this quantity and use their optimality conditions to declare the price they are willing to pay for the good. The firm observes this prices, which can be manipulated to reveal the current level of the demand shock. This acts as a signal about the firm specific constant component of the demand shock. Firms are Bayesian and update their beliefs about this component each period after observing the demand shock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firms face fixed per-period cost of selling into each country. These costs increase with the number of products produced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conditional on entering into a specific market, each period firms choose the number of products to be sold into the market as well as a quantity of each of these goods to maximize the expected value of their one period profits. Firm&#39;s operate in monopolistically competitive markets, so they understand how their quantity decision will impact the market clearing price. However, they do not know the current value of the demand shock, so they form expectations of the price using their current beliefs about the firm specific demand shock. The output of this problem is a quantity for each product as well as an expected profit for each profit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firms continue to add products until the expected profits from adding more varieties (taking into account the fixed costs) are negative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, firms face an entry and exit decision. A firm with productivity &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;φ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; has as state variables the sufficient statistics for their beliefs regarding the firm specific demand shock. They then choose whether or not to enter each market using the expected profit functions we just discussed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Timoshenko looks at a symmetric, stationary equilibrium of this economy. Some properties of this equilibrium are are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The market participation policy is given by a cutoff threshold for the current expected value of the firm specific demand shock in terms of productive and other sufficient statistics. This cutoff is decreasing in productivity and increasing in the precision (inverse of variance).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The quantity adjustment in response to seeing another signal about the demand shock is positive when the posterior mean is sufficiently high and negative when it is lower. The cutoff is a function of the prior mean and variance and the variance of the signal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Profits scale with quantities, so many high signals expands quantities and profits, and causes firms to add new products. A sequence of low signals has the opposite effect: lower quantities and profits leading to dropping products.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Firms posterior precision increases deterministically, meaning asymptotically firms perfectly learn the firm specific component of the demand shocks. This generates age effects in quantity decisions and profits, which in turn generate age effects in adding and dropping products that match the data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If trade costs are lowered, the quantity of all current products is expanded. This is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; supported empirically. In the data, lower trade costs tend to have firms specialize more -- meaning they increase qualities of their most profitable products and scale back on quantities of marginal products.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;quantitative-results&#34;&gt;Quantitative results&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A brief quantitative section is given. The main message is that the model generates more modest values of the number of exporters that engage in product switching, the age dependent survival rate of exporters, and the age dependence of product switching. This suggests that the learning mechanism in the model is significant and supported by the data, but not sufficient to fully explain product switching behavior of Brazilian firms.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Konda and Tsitsiklis (2003) (Actor-critic Algorithms)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/04/19/konda-and-tsitsiklis-2003-actor-critic-algorithms/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/04/19/konda-and-tsitsiklis-2003-actor-critic-algorithms/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a Markov decision process (MDP) is formulated as a dynamic programming problem, the reinforcement learning literature proposes are two classic classes of algorithms to solve them. Let&amp;rsquo;s briefly review these types of algorithms and point out strengths and weaknesses of each.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;actor-only-methods&#34;&gt;1: Actor only methods&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can think of an actor as a fictitious character that operates on a policy rule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I talk about the performance of an actor, I mean the value of following a policy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These methods are often implemented by estimating the gradient of the performance of an actor using simulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two main issues with these &amp;quot;policy iteration&amp;quot;-esque algorithms:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gradient estimators can have high variance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As the policy changes, a new gradient is estimated independently. This means there is no sense of learning from past data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;critic-only-methods&#34;&gt;2: Critic only methods&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can think of a critic operating on either a Q or V value function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These methods rely exclusively on value function approximation and try to learn the solution to Bellman&amp;rsquo;s equation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main issues with critic only methods are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They are indirect in that they do not try to optimize directly over the policy space&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Even with an accurate approximation of the value function, results that guarantee the near-optimality of the corresponding policy are difficult to guarantee.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;main-idea&#34;&gt;Main idea&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper suggests two actor-critic hybrid methods that aim to maintain the best features of each algorithm, while overcoming the shortcomings mentioned above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main idea behind the algorithms is that the critic uses a linearly parameterized approximation scheme and simulation to learn a value function. The actor then uses the learned information to update parameters on the policy function in a direction of performance improvement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Aside to tie back to econ&lt;/em&gt;: This feels like modified policy iteration or Howard&amp;rsquo;s improvement algorithm, but it is different in a few ways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is a learning element to these algorithms, which means we don&amp;rsquo;t have to compute expectations explicitly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We will be learning Q functions, which describe the value of being in a state and taking any feasible action (instead of the V function that describes the value of being in a state and choosing the optimal action).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;algorithms&#34;&gt;Algorithms&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;!-- The algorithms are presented in terms of identifying a randomized stationary
policy. We typically think of a policy function as assigning a unique action to
each state. A randomized stationary policy attaches a probability distribution
over actions to each state. In some sense a standard policy is like a pure
strategy, whereas a randomized stationary is like a mixed strategy. --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The presentation is very technical and relies on assumptions that aren&amp;rsquo;t necessarily applicable to the models we write down, so I won&amp;rsquo;t the paper exactly as it was written. Instead, I will sketch the algorithm and explain the key insight the authors have that makes the algorithm tractable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;setup&#34;&gt;Setup&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will represent the critic using three variables:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A coefficient vector of length &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; that describe a linear parametrization of Q in terms of basis functions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A scalar &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;α&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; that represents the average value of following the actor&amp;rsquo;s policy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A vector of length &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; that represents Sutton&amp;rsquo;s eligibility trace. This vector is used to form a bridge between fixed point methods and Monte Carlo methods&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The actor is represented by a suitable parametric representation of the policy function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;algo&#34;&gt;Algo&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to understand the algorithm, I need to provide two related definitions. A &lt;strong&gt;temporal difference&lt;/strong&gt; is the difference between the current approximation of a variable and a realization of that variable. In other words it is the error in our approximation for a particular sample.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We say we &lt;em&gt;update&lt;/em&gt; parameters or approximations using a &lt;strong&gt;temporal difference&lt;/strong&gt; if the new approximation is the sum of the current approximation and a scaled temporal difference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The algorithm &lt;em&gt;roughly&lt;/em&gt; proceeds as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Initialize the actor and critic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Perform one step updates of the actor and critic as follows:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Because we learn Q, we enter a time period with a particular state and action in hand&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The actor will dictate a new action and we need to simulate a new state, potentially given that action&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The critic&amp;rsquo;s parameters are updated according to:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Average value of policy: temporal difference update (using flow implied by state and action)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Coefficient vector for Q: temporal difference update, scaled by eligibility trace&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Eligibility trace:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The actor&amp;rsquo;s parameter vector is updated using a gradient approach that resembles Newton&amp;rsquo;s method. It takes into account updates to the actor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key insight the authors have that make this algorithm tractable is the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actors have to update a small number of parameters compared to the number of states. So the critic doesn&amp;rsquo;t need to form an approximation over the entire domain of Q, but rather a special projection of the Q onto the space spanned by the actor&amp;rsquo;s parameter vector.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Busoniu, DeSchutter, Babuska(2010) (Approximate dynamic programming and reinforcement learning)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/04/12/busoniu-deschutter-babuska2010-approximate-dynamic-programming-and-reinforcement-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/04/12/busoniu-deschutter-babuska2010-approximate-dynamic-programming-and-reinforcement-learning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This paper provides an overview of various solution concepts that belong to the families of approximate dynamic programming and reinforcement learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will discuss an alternative representation of a dynamic programming that is often used in this literature and provide an overview of some solution methods that are common with this representation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;basics-q-functions&#34;&gt;Basics: Q-functions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In economics, the standard representation of a dynamic programming problem is to define a recursive function &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;V&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; that maps from a state space into the real line. Today I will call &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;V&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; the &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;V&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; function. The &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;V&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; function describes the value of being in a particular state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider an alternative function &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; that maps from the state-action space, into the real line. I will call this the &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;-function. The &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; function describes the value of being in a particular state and choosing a particular action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we do with the &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;V&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;-function, we can express the &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;-function recursively using Bellman&#39;s principle of optimality. The recursive form of the &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;-function is&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q&lt;/em&gt;(&lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;)=&lt;em&gt;E&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;′∼&lt;em&gt;f&lt;/em&gt;(&lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;, ⋅)&lt;/sub&gt;[&lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt;(&lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;,&lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;,&lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;′)+&lt;em&gt;β&lt;/em&gt;max&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;′&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q&lt;/em&gt;(&lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;′,&lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;′)]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can make some basic comparisons between &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;V&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; by studying their recursive representations:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Parameteric representations (i.e. splines or other interpolands) of &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; are more expensive than representations of &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;V&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; because &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; is defined over the state-action space instead of just the state space.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Computing the maximization on the right hand side of &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; is easier than the max on the RHS of &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;V&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;. This is because the expectation is &lt;em&gt;outside&lt;/em&gt; the max in &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, but inside the max for &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;V&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Bellman operator associated with the &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; function is a contraction mapping under the same conditions that Bellman operator associated &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;V&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; is a contraction mapping. When &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&#39;s operator is a contraction mapping, the operators&#39; unique fixed point &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt; is the optimal &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The optimal policy can be easily computed from &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt;: &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;$h^* (s) = \underset{x}{\text{argmax}} Q^* (s, x)$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The optimal &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;V&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;-function can be obtained from &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt;: &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;$V^* = \underset{x}{\max} Q^* (s, x)$&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;computing-q&#34;&gt;Computing Q&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We see that if we can find &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, we can get the value and policy functions we care about as economists. I want to briefly describe a few flavors of algorithms that can be used to compute &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;q-learning&#34;&gt;Q-learning&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Q-learning is classified as an online, model-free algorithm. This means you can update your guess for &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt; whenever new data becomes available. Economists would classify this as a simulation algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s the basics:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start with any initial guess for the &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; function&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then on each iteration &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Given the state action pair on the &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;th iteration (&lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;(&lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;, &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;), the observation of the period &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; return &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, and the state iteration &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt; + 1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt; + 1&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt;...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;... update your guess for &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; using: &lt;br /&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt; + 1&lt;/sub&gt;(&lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;, &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;)=(1 − &lt;em&gt;α&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;)&lt;em&gt;Q&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;(&lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;, &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;)+&lt;em&gt;α&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;(&lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;+&lt;em&gt;β&lt;/em&gt;max&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;′&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;(&lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt; + 1&lt;/sub&gt;,&lt;em&gt;u&lt;/em&gt;′))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notice that the right hand side is a convex combination of the current guess of the &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; function and the right hand side of the &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;-function operator. This is very similar to standard value function iteration, but has the main advantage of not having any expectations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This can be applied to any model for which you have a transition function that defines the state today as a function of the state and action yesterday and a random innovation from a distribution you can sample. Many economic models fit into this framework.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the action space is continuous, you need do a modest alteration of the basic algorithm to ensure asymptotic convergence to &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;approximate-q-iteration&#34;&gt;Approximate Q-iteration&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One strength of this literature is the number of different ways of reducing the dimensionality of a dynamic programming problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Approximate Q-iteration is one example of this type of algorithm. Here instead of operating on the &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;-function directly, we instead operate on a parameterized approximation of the &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;-function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This can be done using linear dependence on coefficients (splines, Chebyshev polynomials) or non-linear parametric approximations (neural nets).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&#39;ll focus on the linearly parametrized version here. We will form an approximation &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;$\hat{Q}(s, x) = \sum_{l=1}^n \phi_l(s, x) \theta_l = \Phi\theta$&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We and talk about a variant of the Q-learning we previously discussed that uses gradient information to update the coefficient vector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s the basic idea:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start with any guess of coefficients &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;θ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then on each iteration &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Given the state action pair on the &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;th iteration (&lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;(&lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;, &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;), the observation of the period &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; return &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, and the state iteration &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt; + 1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt; + 1&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt;...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;... update your guess for &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;θ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; using: &lt;br /&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;$$\theta_{i+1} = \theta_i + \alpha_i \left[r_i + \beta \max_{x&#39;} \hat{Q}_i(s_{i+1}, x&#39;)  - \hat{Q}_i(s_i, x_i)\right] \frac{\partial}{\partial \theta_i} \hat{Q}_i(s_i, x_i)$$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the linear parameterization world we are in this becomes &lt;br /&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;θ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt; + 1&lt;/sub&gt; = &lt;em&gt;θ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; + &lt;em&gt;α&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;[&lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;+&lt;em&gt;β&lt;/em&gt;max&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;′&lt;/sub&gt;(&lt;em&gt;Φ&lt;/em&gt;(&lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt; + 1&lt;/sub&gt;,&lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;′)&lt;em&gt;θ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;)−&lt;em&gt;Φ&lt;/em&gt;(&lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;,&lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;)&lt;em&gt;θ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;]&lt;em&gt;Φ&lt;/em&gt;(&lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;, &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As this is a Q-learning algorithm, the same computational benefits arise here, but now we additionally have the benefit of a potentially vastly reduced computational problem depending on the state-action space the choice of basis functions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>de Farias &amp; van Roy (2003) (The Linear Programming Approach to Approximate Dynamic Programming)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/03/29/de-farias--van-roy-2003-the-linear-programming-approach-to-approximate-dynamic-programming/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/03/29/de-farias--van-roy-2003-the-linear-programming-approach-to-approximate-dynamic-programming/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This paper was published in Operations Research and as such they use a different notation and jargon than economists. I&#39;ll present some of their main results, but in a language and notation that is familiar to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider a typical dynamic programming problem faced by an economic agent, which we summarize by the following Bellman equation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;$$V(x) = \underset{c \in \Gamma(x)}{\max} u(x, c) + \beta E V(x&#39;)$$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now define the natural operator associated with the Bellman, which we call &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;$$T v = \underset{c \in \Gamma(x)}{\max} u(x, c) + \beta E v(x&#39;)$$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For ease of presentation we will directly assume that &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; is a contraction mapping and that &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;v&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; belongs to the set of bounded and continuous functions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;v&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt; be the optimal value function. Under our assumptions &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;v&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt; is the unique fixed point of Bellman&#39;s equation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;mathematical-programs&#34;&gt;Mathematical programs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under our assumptions, the operator &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; is monotonic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means that for any &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;v&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; such that &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;v&lt;/em&gt; ≥ &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;v&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; we have &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;v&lt;/em&gt; ≥ &lt;em&gt;v&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;∀&lt;em&gt;v&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;v&lt;/em&gt; ≤ &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;v&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;v&lt;/em&gt; ≤ &lt;em&gt;v&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Typically this property of our contraction mapping is used to show that value function iteration will converge for any initial guess of &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;v&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;. Today we will use it in a slightly different way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;c&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; be any vector of all positive elements. Consider the mathematical program defined by&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;$$\begin{aligned}&amp;amp;\underset{V}{\min} c&#39;v \\
s.t. &amp;amp; \quad v \ge T v
\end{aligned}$$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the monotonicity of &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; it is easy to see that any &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;v&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; satisfying the constraint must be at least as big at &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;v&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then notice that the objective is to minimize the inner product between a strictly positive vector &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;c&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; and the choice &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;v&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These two facts mean that the unique solution to the programming problem is &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;v&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;linear-program&#34;&gt;Linear program&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I told you that we would use linear programming, but notice that the constraint is nonlinear because &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; is nonlinear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, if we stare at the definition of &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; for long enough we will notice that if we consider the constraint &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;v&lt;/em&gt; ≥ &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;v&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; state by state, (e.g. &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;v&lt;/em&gt;(&lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;)≥&lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;v&lt;/em&gt;(&lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;) we will notice that we can replace the single non-linear constraint per state with a system of linear constraints for each state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This system is defined by enumerating all feasible actions for each state and writing down the right hand side of Bellman&#39;s equation for that state and control. The program looks as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;$$\begin{aligned}&amp;amp;\underset{V}{\min} c&#39;v \\
s.t. &amp;amp; \quad v(x) \ge u(x,c) + \beta \sum_{x&#39;} P(x&#39;| x,c)v(x&#39;) \quad \forall x \in X \; \forall c \in \mathcal{A}_x
\end{aligned}$$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;curse-of-dimensionality&#34;&gt;Curse of dimensionality&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This linear program has an &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; dimensional state with an &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt; * &lt;em&gt;A&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; dimensional constraint matrix. When &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; or &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;A&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; are large, this problem can quickly become subject to the curse of dimensionality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors of this paper propose approximate linear programming as a way to resolve this issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specifically they choose to represent &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;v&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; as the product of a basis matrix and a vector of coefficients &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They then write down a linear program&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;$$\begin{aligned}&amp;amp;\underset{V}{\min} c&#39;\Phi r \\
s.t. &amp;amp; \quad \Phi r(x) \ge u(x,c) + \beta \sum_{x&#39;} P(x&#39;| x,c) \Phi r(x&#39;) \quad \forall x \in X \; \forall c \in \mathcal{A}_x
\end{aligned}$$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notice now that we have swapped out a vector of length &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, for a vector with length equal to the number of columns in the basis matrix. This is something that we have control over, thus we can choose the &amp;quot;size&amp;quot; of this problem. Thus the objective is smaller, but the number of constraints is exactly the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, if we choose each column of &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Φ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; to have finite support (i.e. we use splines), most constraints become inactive and the large constraint matrix becomes sparse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The remainder of the paper, and its main contribution, is to bound the error we are subject to by solving the approximate linear program instead of the exact linear program.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hull (2015) (Approximate dynamic programming with post-decision states as a solution method for dynamic economic models)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/03/22/hull-2015-approximate-dynamic-programming-with-post-decision-states-as-a-solution-method-for-dynamic-economic-models/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/03/22/hull-2015-approximate-dynamic-programming-with-post-decision-states-as-a-solution-method-for-dynamic-economic-models/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This paper presents a stochastic simulation method for solving dynamic economic models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ideas in this paper lean on a literature sometimes known as approximate dynamic programming and can enable us to solve models with many state variables and non-convexities in objectives and constraints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My intent is to summarize the core theoretical ideas behind the algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;main-idea-post-decision-states&#34;&gt;Main idea: Post decision states&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;notation-classic-bellman-equation&#34;&gt;Notation: classic Bellman equation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider a stationary economic model where at time &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; the state is summarized by a vector &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; of endogenous state variables and a vector &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; of exogenous state variables.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The optimization problem of an agent is often summarized by a Bellman equation of the form&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;V&lt;/em&gt;(&lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;, &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;)=&lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;c&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;u&lt;/em&gt;(&lt;em&gt;c&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;)+&lt;em&gt;β&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;E&lt;/em&gt;[&lt;em&gt;V&lt;/em&gt;(&lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt; + 1&lt;/sub&gt;, &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt; + 1&lt;/sub&gt;)]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;subject to&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt; + 1&lt;/sub&gt; = &lt;em&gt;f&lt;/em&gt;(&lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;, &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;, &lt;em&gt;c&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;), &lt;em&gt;c&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; ∈ &lt;em&gt;Γ&lt;/em&gt;(&lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;, &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;), &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt; + 1&lt;/sub&gt; = &lt;em&gt;g&lt;/em&gt;(&lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;, &lt;em&gt;ϵ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt; + 1&lt;/sub&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;post-decision-state-value-function&#34;&gt;Post-decision state value function&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that that the transition function for the endogenous state takes &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;, &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, and &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;c&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; and emits &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt; + 1&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt;. We can think of &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt; + 1&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; being chosen at the end of period &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, meaning after the controls &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;c&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; have been decided.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the standard (or pre-decision) Bellman equation, we have that the state at time &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; is the endogenous state defined at the end of period &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt; − 1&lt;/span&gt; and the exogenous state realized at the start of period &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will now consider a different representation of the state vector that couples the endogenous state defined at the end of period &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt; − 1&lt;/span&gt; with the exogenous state realized at the start of period &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt; − 1&lt;/span&gt;. That is we will consider &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt; − 1&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, which is known as the post-decision state at time &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt; − 1&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;V&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;(&lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;, &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt; − 1&lt;/sub&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; be the value of having post-decision state &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt; − 1&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; in period &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt; − 1&lt;/span&gt;. This is the maximum expected, discounted utility an agent can achieve after controls have been selected in period &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt; − 1&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;c&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt; − 1&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; is not chosen until &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt; − 1&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; is realized, we know that &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;V&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;(&lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;, &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt; − 1&lt;/sub&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; is equal to the expectation of the maximum expected, discounted utility the agent will receive after &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; arrives. That is, we can write&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;V&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;(&lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;, &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt; − 1&lt;/sub&gt;)=&lt;em&gt;E&lt;/em&gt;[&lt;em&gt;V&lt;/em&gt;(&lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;, &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;)|&lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;, &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt; − 1&lt;/sub&gt;],&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;V&lt;/em&gt;(&lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;, &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; is the pre-decision Bellman equation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It follows that we can write&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;V&lt;/em&gt;(&lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;, &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;)=&lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;c&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; + &lt;em&gt;β&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;V&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;(&lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt; + 1&lt;/sub&gt;, &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These equations can be manipulated to produce the recursive form of the post-decision state Bellman equation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;V&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;(&lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;, &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt; − 1&lt;/sub&gt;)=&lt;em&gt;E&lt;/em&gt;[&lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;c&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;u&lt;/em&gt;(&lt;em&gt;c&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;)+&lt;em&gt;β&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;V&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;(&lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt; + 1&lt;/sub&gt;, &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;)|&lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;, &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt; − 1&lt;/sub&gt;].&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notice that the expectation is &lt;em&gt;outside&lt;/em&gt; the max operator, meaning that the maximization problem is deterministic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;algorithm&#34;&gt;Algorithm&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we have the post-decision state Bellman equation, the algorithm is fairly straightforward. I will present the algorithm from the paper in the context of Markov exogenous processes, but I believe it is incorrectly specified. I&#39;ll discuss how I&#39;d change it later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Setup
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Discretize endogenous state space&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choose a simulation length &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choose initial endogenous and exogenous states&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Construct an initial guess for the value function at the discritized endogenous and exogenous states.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Iterations
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Construct a time series of Exogenous states for t=1, 2, ..., T&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For time &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt; = 1, 2, ..., &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; perform the following 3 steps:
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choose controls &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;c&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; to maximize the term inside the expectation on the RHS of &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;V&lt;/em&gt;(&lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;, &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt; − 1)&lt;/span&gt;. To do this we need to using the value function from the previous iteration for the future value function&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compute the expectation implicitly by updating the guess of the value function using a convex combination of the previous iteration&#39;s value function and the value computed above&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using the chosen controls and realization of exogenous state, apply the endogenous transition equation to iterate the endogenous state forward one period&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Convergence:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Check a convergence criterion that compares the discretized value function across multiple iterations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If converged, return the discretized value function and run a regression on the time series to obtain a policy function from the time series of controls&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;comments-on-the-algorithm&#34;&gt;Comments on the algorithm&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are a few comments about the algorithm:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Because the expectation operator is outside the max operator, we don&#39;t have to spend time computing expectations when solving the optimization problem in each period of the simulation. This speeds up computation quite a bit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Expectations are computed implicitly when we update our guess for the post-decision state value function&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My compliant&lt;/strong&gt; I think it is incorrect to re-generate a time series of exogenous states on each iteration. Doing so will not allow the algorithm to ever converge as the updated value function in iteration &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; is dependent on the randomness from the exogenous simulation in period &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using the same simulated time series for exogenous states in every iteration (as in other simulation algorithms in the literature) will allow this algorithm to converge; subject to a particular exogenous path. To ensure that the solution is accurate for the underlying data generating process and not just the simulation you use, make sure that the length of the time series is large.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Achdou, Han, Lasry, Lions, Moll (2015) (Hetergenous agent models in continuous time)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/03/08/achdou-han-lasry-lions-moll-2015-hetergenous-agent-models-in-continuous-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/03/08/achdou-han-lasry-lions-moll-2015-hetergenous-agent-models-in-continuous-time/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This paper looks at the class of equations used to represent and solve heterogenous agent models in continuous time and presents a solution approach that is efficient and tractable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;model&#34;&gt;Model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few models were presented in the paper. Here we&amp;rsquo;ll take the simplest one: a continuous time version of the Huggett economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this economy there are a continuum of individuals that are heterogeneous in their wealth and income.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Individuals value streams of consumption using CRRA preferences and a constant discount factor &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;ρ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Income is exogenous and is given in units of the consumption good. Wealth is accumulates via a risk free bond. Wealth evolves deterministically via&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;d&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; = (&lt;em&gt;z&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;+&lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;−&lt;em&gt;c&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;)&lt;em&gt;d&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Households are subject to a fixed, exogenous borrowing constraint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Income evolves stochastically and follows a two state Poisson process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only price in the economy is the interest rate. It will be determined by a zero net supply condition on the bond.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because agents are heterogeneous, a state variable in this economy is the joint distribution of agents across wealth and income.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;theoretical-contributions&#34;&gt;Theoretical contributions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors make various theoretical contributions. We&amp;rsquo;ll review those before moving on to the described solution approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Agents in this economy are never borrowing constrained on the interior of the wealth state space. This means that the distribution is smooth everywhere, except possibly at the constraint. Very not true in discrete time. (multiple mass points in discrete economy). Also very easy to implement as they the only place the borrowing constraint enters the problem is in boundary conditions for the system of PDEs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the stationary equilibrium (constant &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;), agents hit the constraint at a rate the authors characterize analytically&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An analytic characterization of the shape of both tails of the wealth distribution. Difficult to do in discrete time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Equilibrium interest rate has a tight link to the number of constraint agents&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And an existence proof&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;solution-method&#34;&gt;Solution method&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The economy we discussed above (and a class of other economies) can be boiled down to a coupled system of two PDEs:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An HJB equation that describes the optimization behavior of agents&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A Kolmogorov Forward (or Fokker Plank) equation that describes the evolution of the distribution of agents&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the main steps of the algorithm they describe to compute the stationary equilibrium of the model:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Given an interest rate, solve the HJB equation using a finite difference method (details below). Output is a savings rate function for each type&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Given the savings rules, solve the Kolmogorov Forward equation for the distribution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Given the distribution, aggregate the savings rule and check the equilibrium (market clearing) condition(s).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the equilibrium condition(s) are not met, adjust r and iterate until convergence&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This algorithm is very standard, but there are a few key features here that you may not find in similar discrete time algorithms:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The distribution is characterized by a well known PDE &amp;ndash; it is often very straightforward to solve&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is an established literature for solving HJB equations. The authors are able to leverage theoretical results (Barles and Souganidis (1991)) that guarantee the convergence of their finite difference scheme.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Borrowing constraint is completely handled via a boundary condition &amp;ndash; something that already required for solving the PDEs, not something additional you need to build the algorithm around.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Costinot, Rodriguez, Werning (2016) (Micro to Macro: Optimal Trade Policy with Firm Heterogeneity)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/03/01/costinot-rodriguez-werning-2016-micro-to-macro-optimal-trade-policy-with-firm-heterogeneity/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/03/01/costinot-rodriguez-werning-2016-micro-to-macro-optimal-trade-policy-with-firm-heterogeneity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This paper extends the Meltiz framework to allow for optimal tariff policies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;model&#34;&gt;Model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This model extends a two country Melitz framework in two ways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Allows for heterogeneity in variable and fixed costs. This will be a policy instrument where governments can set firm specific tariffs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The representative consumer in each country has a constant elasticity of substitution across all varieties procued within a country, but that elasticity can differ across countries.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;preferences&#34;&gt;Preferences&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In each country there is a representative consumer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The consumer has CES preferences over all varieties in both countries, but the CES parameter might differ across countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;technology&#34;&gt;Technology&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Household inelastically supply a fixed amount of aggregate labor to their own country. Firms pay households a country specific wage for each unit of labor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a continuum of firms in each country, indexed by their productivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each firm takes in labor and produces consumption good. Labor demand for each firm is affine in the quantity produced. The slope and intercept coefficients can be arbitrary functions of productivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Markets&lt;/strong&gt; Firms sell their goods in a monopolistically competitive market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;taxes&#34;&gt;Taxes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will consider a cost structure where each firm can potentially face both an import tariff in the consumer&#39;s country and an export subsidy in the firm&#39;s country. Note that a negative tariff acts like an import subsidy and a negative export subsidy acts like an export tax.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All tax revenues are rebated lump sum to the consumer in the country where the revenues are collected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;equilibrium&#34;&gt;Equilibrium&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will consider a decentralized equilibrium in which&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;consumers maximize their utility subject to their budget constraint&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;firms choose their output to maximize their profits taking their residual demand curves a given&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;firms optimally choose to enter domestic and export markets, based on productivity and costs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The government&#39;s budget is balanced in each country (all tax revenues are rebated to HH)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;solution&#34;&gt;Solution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I felt the solution technique was interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors consider a special case of the model just described where the government in country &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;H&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; is strategic and the the government in country &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;F&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; is passive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means that the &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;H&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; government chooses tariffs and subsidies to maximize home consumer&#39;s utility, whereas all taxes and subsidies in &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;F&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; are zero.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The home government&#39;s problem is written as a planning problem where the planner chooses taxes, subsidies, prices, and quantities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;planning-problems&#34;&gt;Planning problems&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To solve this model the authors use a three step procedure:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Solve the problem of minimizing labor cost, subject to producing &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;H&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;H&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; units of aggregate consumption for the home consumer and &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;H&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;F&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; units for the foreign consumer.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This problem is infinite dimensional (a continuum of firms) and non-smooth (kinks because of fixed costs)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;However, the objective and constraint are additively separable in the controls (quantities for each firm type) so the problem can be solved firm by firm and market by market using a Lagrangian approach.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This breaks down the difficult original problem one dimensional subproblems and an conditions on Lagrange multipliers such that the aggregate production constraint holds&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This problem has a unique solution that is characterized in closed form&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Solve the problem of minimizing the cost of importing one unit of aggregate goods from country &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;F&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, subject to aggregate imports being &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;F&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;H&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt;.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The control here is import quantities for each foreign firm.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The problem faces the same issues as before, but is also additively separable in the control, so it can be solved using a similar Lagrangian approach&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The solution to this problem is also unique and characterized in closed form&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Solve the problem of optimally choosing &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;H&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;H&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;H&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;F&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, and &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;F&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;H&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; to maximize the home consumer&#39;s utility, subject to the constrains on aggregate quantities implied by aggregating the results of the previous two micro problems
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The solution is again unique and characterized in closed form&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The key output of this problem is that the optimal behavior can be characterized only by manipulating the terms of trade. This will be important for implementing this solution using taxes in the next section.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;implementation&#34;&gt;Implementation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the solution to the decentralized planner&#39;s problem in hand, the authors then describe how to implement this equilibrium using a variety of possible tariff and subsidy schemes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will focus on the equilibrium with a fully flexible tax system that allows the home government to choose tariffs and subsidies for each producer/consumer pair.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results can be summarized as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The ratio of home to home subsidy and home to home tariffs is constant for all productivity levels.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The home to foreign subsidy is constant for all productivity levels&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The foreign to home tariff discriminates across productivity levels.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For all foreign producers above a certain productivity level, per unit tariffs are flat.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For all foreign producers below this level who still choose to export in this equilibrium tariffs are lower, but strictly increasing in the export profitability of the firm.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The set of firms who face the discriminatory tariffs are the most interesting part of this equilibrium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The firms in this set are have export profits that are exactly equal to the fixed costs of production in the foreign to home market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the decentralized equilibrium, the planner found it optimal to adjust the quantity demanded from these firms relative firms for which the constraint was slack, &lt;strong&gt;to ensure that binding firms are willing to produce and export strictly positive amounts&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way to implement his feature of the first-best equilibrium using taxes, is to have tariffs scale one for one with the profitability of the firms whose export profit constraint binds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two extensions of the Melitz model (heterogenous trade costs and market specific CES parameters) generated one main departure from the Melitz equilibrium: an optimal one-sided tariff and subsidy policy that discriminates against low productivity foreign exporters.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Eaton, Eslava, Jinkins, Krizan, Tybout (2014) (A search and learning model of export dynamics)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/02/16/eaton-eslava-jinkins-krizan-tybout-2014-a-search-and-learning-model-of-export-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/02/16/eaton-eslava-jinkins-krizan-tybout-2014-a-search-and-learning-model-of-export-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;h1 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A primarily empirical paper that studies how allowing exporting firms to learn about demand for their product impacts firm dynamics in a Melitz style trade model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;data-and-stylized-facts&#34;&gt;Data and stylized facts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s start with the data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data set used in this paper describes all imports by US buyers from Colombian exporters from 1992-2009. The source is the U.S. Census Bureau’s Longitudinal Foreign Trade Transactions Database (LFTTD).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using this data, the authors report the following stylized facts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;About 80% of Colombian exporter/US importer matches are 1-1, meaning the Colombian firm has no other US buyers and the US firm only buys from a single Colombian firm.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;About 70% of matches dissolve after one period. There are several additional features behind this fact:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If a match does survive the into a second period, there is a significantly higher chance it will survive into the third (about 50%). This trend continues as the duration of the match increases.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The survival probability of a new match increases with first year sales volume.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;These facts suggest that there are many Colombian firms who merely &amp;quot;test the US waters&amp;quot; and export a small volume, find the conditions unfavorable, and exit. This might suggest these firms are trying to learn about foreign demand.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;model&#34;&gt;Model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let&amp;rsquo;s turn to the theoretical model. The model is set in continuous time and will feature Columbian firms who sell domestically and to US importers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;firm-pricing-problem&#34;&gt;Firm pricing problem&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each Colombian firm competes monopolistically and seeks to maximize total profits. The details of the pricing problem solved by the firms are not given, but rather the authors jump to the Melitz result: prices are set to a constant markup over marginal costs. In this setting the profits of a firm can be written as a multiplicative function of three components:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A macroeconomic state that is common to all firms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Firm productivity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A time-varying match specific demand shifter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;relationships&#34;&gt;Relationships&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At each instant in time the seller maintains relationships with an endogenous number of buyers. These relationships are the product of a search process that will be outlined shortly. The matches dissolve exogenously at a constant rate &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;δ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; or if the seller no longer finds it profitable to pay a constant fixed cost &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;F&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; to maintain the relationship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the match is kept alive, it may be hit by one of three events:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With a constant hazard &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;λ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;em&gt;b&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt; the buyer places another order&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With a hazard &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;q&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;′&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;em&gt;X&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt; the macro state will jump to a new level&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With a hazard &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;q&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;y&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;y&lt;/em&gt;′&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;em&gt;Y&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt; the match specific demand shifter will jump to a new level&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the shocks to macro and idiosyncratic states are Markov, the stopping time characterizing when one event occurs is distributed exponentially. This allows the authors to write the firms expected profit recursively and obtain expectations in closed form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;learning&#34;&gt;Learning&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sellers conduct search in domestic and foreign markets. When searching in a particular market &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, sellers understand that a constant fraction &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;θ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt; of potential buys will form a match.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each seller draws &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;θ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;em&gt;h&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;θ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;em&gt;f&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt; before meeting with any clients and the draws remain fixed over time. All draws of &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;θ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; come independently from a beta distribution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sellers are assumed to have met with many domestic firms and know &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;θ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;em&gt;h&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt;. They will; however, have to learn about &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;θ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;em&gt;f&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt; by meeting with many firms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a given level of &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;θ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;em&gt;f&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, the probability that a random sample of &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; potential foreign buyers will result in &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; matches is distributed binomally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The beta and binomial distributions form a conjugate pair, so after &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; are realized, the posterior for &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;θ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;em&gt;f&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt; is known in closed form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;search&#34;&gt;Search&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final component of the model is the search problem. Each seller will continuously choose a market specific hazard rate &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt; with which they meet with a potential buyer. At the moment of the meeting, the firm pays a flow cost of &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;c&lt;/em&gt;(&lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;, where &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; is still the number of successful previous matches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The search problem for a firm with a specific productivity and matching efficiency can be written recursively with states being &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; and the macro state &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;. The expectations in this recursive formulation are again over the stopping time of seller events, which means they can also be written in closed form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The optimal search hazard rate for each firm in both markets can be characterized in closed form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;empirical-model&#34;&gt;Empirical Model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To implement this model empirically, the authors impose the following additional structure:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A specific form for the search cost function&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Distributions for all exogenous states (seller productivity, and macro/micro states) are all assumed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The data is uninformative regarding the rate of time discount for sellers and the demand elasticity, so values for these parameters are directly assumed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The distribution of the states is a set of independent Ehrenfest diffusion processes. This process is special because it converges to the well known Ornstein-Uhlenbeck process as the spacing between grid points in the state space converges to zero&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;estimation&#34;&gt;Estimation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Estimation is broken into 2 stages:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;estimating-the-jump-process-for-macro-states&#34;&gt;Estimating the jump process for macro states&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They proxy &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; in each market as real expenditures on manufacturing goods in that country. Their distributional assumption for the macro states allow them summarize the distribution in terms of a jump size and hazard rate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;indirect-inference&#34;&gt;Indirect inference&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rest of the estimation happens via indirect inference on the closed form results form the theoretical model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The parameters are estimated to minimize distance between moments generated by the model and corresponding moments in the data. The data features that are targeted include&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Distribution of home and foreign sales&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Distribution of clients across exporters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sales per client, conditioned on the number of clients&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An autoregression of log domestic sales&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Transition probabilities in the number of clients&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Exporter exit hazard by duration in foreign market&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Match death probabilities and match sales&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;basic-results&#34;&gt;Basic results&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many parameters, so I won&amp;rsquo;t enumerate how well the model does at targeting each parameter. The overall results are that the estimates match the signs of all empirical moments and the magnitude of most.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some interpretation of the coefficients is helpful:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mature (5+ years) matches fail with a probability of 40%, but the estimated exogenous separation rate is only 27%. This suggests that the idiosyncratic demand shift shocks impact long-run match survival.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On average, the success rate of matches is 0.18. However, the standard deviation of this estimate is 0.176, suggesting that there is significant room for learning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Network effects are very strong. This is summarized by the search cost falling sharply as the number of successful matches rises.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finally, the estimation also suggests that the network effects are strongest for sellers getting their first successful match (suggests that search costs are concave in the number of matches).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;experiments&#34;&gt;Experiments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors then do a few experiments to further probe the model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;no-learning-model&#34;&gt;No-learning model&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They first consider a no learning model where firms are assumed to know both &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;θ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;em&gt;h&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;θ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;em&gt;f&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt; with certainty at the onset of the model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main impact of this model restriction is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The exit of inexperienced exports is lower. This is driven both by having low &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;θ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;em&gt;f&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt; sellers not try to learn about foreign demand and by no learning based exit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To overcome this and still match seller exit rates, exogenous separation probability doubles from 0.26 to 0.52.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Niepmann (2013) (Banking across borders)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/02/16/niepmann-2013-banking-across-borders/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/02/16/niepmann-2013-banking-across-borders/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;intro&#34;&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This introduces heterogenous banks into a general equilibrium trade model in the flavor of Melitz. There are also empirical exercises that show that the model can generate some features of German banking data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;model&#34;&gt;Model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will describe the model in two stages:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Closed economy, where we will characterize economic setting and the optimization problem of each agent.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open economy, where combine 2 closed economies and allow them to trade&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;closed-economy&#34;&gt;Closed economy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The economy consists of the following agents:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A continuum of capitalists of measure &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;K&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;. Capitalists can choose to become bankers or depositors.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A banker has two roles (the optimization problem will be described later):
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Channel capital from depositors to firms and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Monitor the firms they lend to. Bankers earn a return &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;R&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; on all capital they lend to firms (their own, plus that collected from depositors)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A depositor lends their capital endowment to banks and earn a return &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;R&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;em&gt;D&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &amp;lt; =&lt;em&gt;R&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; on their investment. &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;R&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;em&gt;D&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt; is an equilibrium object. Preferences dictate that they then consume all that they have&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A continuum of potential entrepreneurs that run firms.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Firms are perfectly competitive and operate a production technology that exhibits constant returns to scale in capital and labor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They rent capital and labor and seek to maximize revenues less input costs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Firms have a random probability of being productive. If they are productive, they produce and those who supplied capital and labor are paid their rents. If they are not productive, output is zero and those who supplied capital and labor get nothing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A continuum of workers of measure &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;L&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; that inelastically supply labor to the firms and consume all labor income with linear utility.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So; the depositor, worker, and firm problems are all trivial. Bankers are the interesting agents in this model, and we will describe their problem now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The model consists of two time periods&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the first time period the following happens:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Capitalists draw a monitoring cost from a uniform distribution and then choose to become either a banker or depositors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Depositors then lend all their capital to banks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bankers collect capital from depositors and then make two choices: how much to lend to which firms and whether or not to monitor those firms:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The objective of bankers is to maximize the returns they earn, net of payouts to depositors and monitoring costs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As stated above, parameters are such that the banker always chooses to monitor all firms. To credibly commit to monitoring, the banker invests his own capital into the firms he lends to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Profit maximization boils down to maximizing the number of firms the banker lends to. This is a finite number because the banker has finite personal capital.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then in the second period&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Firm production is realized&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rents are paid to banks and workers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Banks pay creditors at a rate &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;R&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;em&gt;d&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt; (all depositors earn the same rate), keeping the rest&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Workers, depositors, and bankers then consume everything they are left with (note all consumption must come out of produced good &amp;ndash; i.e. do not value capital or labor for consumption)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;equilibrium&#34;&gt;Equilibrium&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In equilibrium there is free entry to become a banker. This boils down to having a cutoff in monitoring costs that says all capitalists with monitoring cost above the cutoff become depositors while all others become bankers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second equilibrium condition is that all capital in the economy is used in production.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These two conditions admit a semi-analytical solution for the cutoff monitoring cost and rate of return paid to depositors &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;R&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;em&gt;d&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;open-economy&#34;&gt;Open economy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the open economy there are two countries that typically differ in endowment of capital and labor as well as distribution over monitoring costs. Workers, firms, and depositors only operate within their home country &amp;ndash; bankers are allowed to interact across the border.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bankers can choose to raise deposits at home and abroad as well as invest in domestic or foreign firms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;International bankers face an variable &amp;quot;iceberg&amp;quot; costs where their return is a fraction less than one of what a banker from the foreign country would earn. Also payout costs to foreign depositors are a fraction higher than similar costs for domestic depositors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Operating internationally also has associated fixed costs that come in 3 varieties:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is one fixed cost associated with becoming an international lender&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Another (higher) fixed cost for bankers who with to borrow across the border&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A third (highest) fixed cost associated with foreign direct investment where a banker establishes a foreign affiliate and then interacts through the affiliate and faces no variable costs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;equilibrium-1&#34;&gt;Equilibrium&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Equilibrium behavior in this model is similar in spirit to the equilibrium of Melitz: lower cost bankers will&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take on higher fixed costs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have a larger throughput (lend to more firms)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Earn higher profits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The author proves a unique equilibrium exists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;simplified-model&#34;&gt;Simplified model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The general version of the model is quite complicated. Each banker has 7 potential profit streams (lend domestic capital to foreign firms, lend foreign capital to foreign firms, lend foreign capital to domestic firms, those three repeated but via foreign affiliates, and pure domestic profits).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So consider a simplified version where we assume that factor endowments are such that bankers in country 1 earn a higher return than bankers in country 2 AND bankers in country 1 are more efficient than those in country 2 (have a lower lower bound on the uniform distribution from which costs are drawn).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this case bankers in country 2 will operate only domestically, become international lenders, or operate via foreign direct investment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bankers in country 1 will operate domestically, become international borrowers, or operate via FDI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;experiment&#34;&gt;Experiment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider an experiment where we compare the equilibrium outcomes when countries must live in autarky to the open economy equilibrium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few things will happen:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The returns for bankers in the two countries will move closer to one another (that is the country with low returns will have higher returns than in autarky). This is driven by capital flowing into the higher return country, but not all the way to set returns in the two countries equal because of the fixed costs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The cutoff for entry into domestic markets has an asymmetric impact.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the more productive country the cutoff rises (loosens) and more banks enter. These bankers are more efficient than the foreign ones and are able to displace less efficient bankers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Banks that operate internationally out of either country become larger.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For the borrowers in the high return/productivity country, the larger balance sheet is driven by access to reduced funding costs (rate paid to depositors falls)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For lenders in the less productive country, this is driven by access to markets with higher returns.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;empirics&#34;&gt;Empirics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The author also conducts an empirical analysis using data on the foreign assets and liabilities of all (1998) German banks for a particular year (2005).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reported findings support the predictions of the model:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The probability that a bank has foreign assets/liabilities and net FDI increase with the size of domestic business and efficiency.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Larger banks also hold more foreign assets and liabilities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fixed costs are a key component to foreign operations of banks. Only larger banks can overcome the fixed costs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Das, Roberts, Tybout (2007) (Market entry costs, producer heterogeneity, and export dynamics)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/02/09/das-roberts-tybout-2007-market-entry-costs-producer-heterogeneity-and-export-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/02/09/das-roberts-tybout-2007-market-entry-costs-producer-heterogeneity-and-export-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;intro&#34;&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper takes an empirical look at a variant of the Melitz model from last week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;model&#34;&gt;Model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assumptions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Domestic and foreign product markets are monopolistically competitive and segmented. In Melitz we got segmentation from CRS production.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Marginal&lt;/em&gt; costs do not respond to output shocks: domestic shocks do not impact optimal export levels&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Firms are heterogeneous in marginal production costs and foreign demand functions (so profits differ)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Future exchange rate, production costs, and foreign demand shifters are unkown, but Markov&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Firms must pay an up-front cost to enter export market in addition to per period fixed operating costs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a firm already in the export market, export profits are characterized by log-linear (Cobb Douglass in levels) function of firm-specific characteristics, the real exchange rate, and a random disturbance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The disturbance term is modeled as the sum of &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; independent AR(1) processes, which means it is equivalent to an ARMA(m, m-1) process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The actual profit for a firm is this profit just described less fixed costs. For a firm that is already in the export market, these are a constant fixed cost. For forms that are just deciding to export, this is the same constant fixed cost plus an additional sunk cost for becoming and exporter. The sunk cost makes this model dynamic, because the return to becoming an exporter today includes the option value of being able to continue exporting without having to pay the sunk cost again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;data&#34;&gt;Data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data used in the estimation is on Columbian firms from 1981-1991 in three industries: leather products, knitted fabrics, and basic chemicals. For each industry, the data set includes plant and year specific information on total costs, domestic sales revenue, and realized export revenue. The data also includes plant-specific information such as location, size, business type.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recall that the model was written in terms of firm profits, but that the data set includes information on revenues. The authors use the firm&amp;rsquo;s equilibrium pricing rule (constand markup over marginal cost) to create a link between revenues and profits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors also use data on the real effective exchange rate over the same time horizon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following provides a map between model and data:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The plant-specific demand elasticities are identified by plant-specific ratios of total revenues to total variable costs and by the fraction of revenues that come from exporting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The revenue function parameters are identified by variation in export revenues among incumbent exporters.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sunk entry costs are identified by differences in exporting frequencies across plants that have comparable expected profit streams, but differ in terms of whether they exported in the previous period&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finally, given profit streams and sunk costs, the frequency of exit among firms with positive gross profit streams identifies fixed costs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;estimation&#34;&gt;Estimation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The parameters of the model are estimated using a type II Tobit likelihood function, generalized to handle features of this model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Features requiring generalizations are&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Serially correlated disturbances&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;endogenous initial export conditions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;incidental parameter (demand elasticities).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The likelihood is not globally concave, so point estimates might be difficult to obtain. So, the authors employ a Metropolis Hastings algorithm and characterize the posterior distribution of the model&amp;rsquo;s parameters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;priors&#34;&gt;Priors&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As they employ MCMC methods, the authors need to specify prior distributions for all model parameters. The authors assume that all parameters are independent, thus the prior is the product of univariate priors for each parameter. They choose very diffuse priors for all model parameters except foreign demand elasticities, where they ensure that prior and posterior have mean bounded above by unity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some basic results in line with conventional thinking:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Firms with large domestic revenues typically stand to profit more from exporting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The elasticity of profits with respect to the real exchange rate is very high&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is evidence for strong serial correlation in profit shocks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Larger producers face lower &lt;em&gt;average&lt;/em&gt; sunk cost to entering export market.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;option-value&#34;&gt;Option value&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I think is the most novel finding&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The probability of remaining in the export market roughly 85% on average, with slight variation across industries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because the authors estimated a &lt;em&gt;dynamic&lt;/em&gt; model, they are able to measure the option value of entering in one period and not having to re-pay sunk costs in the next.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They find that the option value is the largest component of export value for most producers&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means at least two things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Modeling implication: Considering the dynamic components of the export entry decision are crucial to get Melitz flavor models to match the data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Policy implications: Changes in option values (perhaps due to changes in expectations about future market conditions) can induce large changes in exporter decisions, even when short run profits are unchanged.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second finding suggests that policies that wish to induce changes in export market participation should aim to adjust the expectation about future market conditions (e.g. expected changes in real interest rates) &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; directly subsidize the export fixed costs (sunk and/or fixed).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Melitz 2003 (The impact of trade on intra-industry reallocations and aggregate industry productivity)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/02/02/melitz-2003-the-impact-of-trade-on-intra-industry-reallocations-and-aggregate-industry-productivity/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/02/02/melitz-2003-the-impact-of-trade-on-intra-industry-reallocations-and-aggregate-industry-productivity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;intro&#34;&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An early paper that introduced a now common framework for thinking about firm entry, export decision, and exit in trade models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;model&#34;&gt;Model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll describe the model in two stages:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A closed economy version of the model with a single country&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An open economy version with many similar countries&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;closed-economy&#34;&gt;Closed economy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;consumers&#34;&gt;Consumers&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a representative consumer with CES a utility function over a continuum of goods. The elasticity of substitution between any two goods is &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;σ&lt;/em&gt; &amp;gt; 1&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can apply Dixit Stiglitz type analysis to model this consumer&amp;rsquo;s choice as choosing only the aggregate, with an associated price. The demand an expenditure on individual varieties is then a function of the aggregated consumption good, aggregate price, and variety prices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;firms&#34;&gt;Firms&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a continuum of firms, who each produce a single variety demanded by the consumer. Production is a function of only labor, which is inelastically supplied at an aggregate level of &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;L&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Technology is characterized by a cost function with constant marginal costs and a fixed overhead cost. This results in labor being an affine function in quantity: &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;l&lt;/em&gt; = &lt;em&gt;f&lt;/em&gt; + &lt;em&gt;q&lt;/em&gt;/&lt;em&gt;φ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;. Here &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;φ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; characterizes the productivity of the firm. Higher productivity is interpreted as producing an identical variety at a lower marginal cost. This allows us to distinguish firms not by the variety they produce, but by their productivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Optimal pricing is the standard constant markup over marginal cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firm revenue and profits can also be expressed in terms of the aggregate expenditure and price from the consumer problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results are that more productive firms are have higher output and revenues, charge a lower price, and earn more profits than less productive firms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;firm-entry-and-exit&#34;&gt;Firm entry and exit&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is an unbounded pool of ex ante identical prospective entrants into the industry. Each firm must pay a fixed entry cost (labor units) to draw a productivity from a distribution &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;g&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;. This productivity remains constant throughout the life of the firm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After receiving its productivity draw a firm can either exit immediately or begin producing. Once a firm decides to produce, there is an exogenous probability &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;δ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; that the firm will be forced to exit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because there are no changes in productivity, the firm&amp;rsquo;s entry decision is static and characterized by a cutoff threshold &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;φ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt;. At &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;φ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt; a firm is indifferent between entering or not. All firms who draw &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;φ&lt;/em&gt; &amp;gt; &lt;em&gt;φ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt; choose to enter; others exit. These firms all earn non-negative profits in equilibrium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To close the economy, we also must consider a free entry condition. This condition says that the average value of entering net of entry costs must be zero.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;equilibrium&#34;&gt;Equilibrium&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There exists a unique equilibrium in this model in which aggregate variables are constant across time. This equilibrium can be understood by a single figure:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- ![Melitz equilibrium](/Users/sglyon/Research/SargentReadingGroup/images/melitz_eqm.png) --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;φ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; on the horizontal axis and firm profits on the vertical axis. Then we put two lines in this space:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &amp;quot;zero profit cutoff&amp;quot;, which characterizes average profits as a function of the cutoff productivity. This will be a downward sloping line&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The free entry condition: expresses average profits as an increasing function of cutoff productivity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Melitz proves that these lines always intersect exactly once, and the intersection is at the point (&lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;φ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;$\bar{\pi}$&lt;/span&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;open-economy&#34;&gt;Open economy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now consider a world where there are &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; additional countries, identical to the one we have been studying, with which our country can trade. In order to trade internationally, each country must pay a fixed cost to enter the export market and a variable trade cost (iceberg cost) per unit of export. These export costs are symmetric.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;equilibrium-1&#34;&gt;Equilibrium&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Equilibrium in this setup is very similar to before. The exogenous environment for individual firms remains unchanged. Symmetric export costs imply that a firm will either choose to export to all foreign countries, or no foreign countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, because a firm&amp;rsquo;s productivity is unchanged after the initial draw, the entry and export decisions are static and each is characterized by a cutoff. The entry cutoff is the same as before. The export cutoff &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;φ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;?&lt;em&gt;φ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt; is characterized by the productivity that sets profits from foreign markets to zero.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;impact-of-trade&#34;&gt;Impact of trade&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will consider one experiment. Suppose a country initially starts in autarky and then is opened to trade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When this happens, the zero profit condition curve (downward sloping one) will shift up and the entry cutoff and average firm profits will both increase. Some firms who did enter in autarky will be forced to exit. Furthermore, only firms with productivity above the export cutoff will enter the export market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will have a number of effects on equilibrium aggregates:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The number of domestic firms decreases (cutoff higher)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Domestic consumers have access to foreign varieties.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Typically this leads consumers to have access to more total varieties. Thus, consumer welfare rises as does aggregate firm profits because of the higher average productivity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When trade costs are high, opening the economy might lead to a net &lt;em&gt;decrease&lt;/em&gt; in the varieties available to consumers (reducing welfare). However, Melitz shows that even in this case the welfare gain from higher average productivity dominates this welfare loss.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why does trade cause less productive firms to exit?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might think it is because domestic firms now face more competition from foreign ones. This heightened competition would lower prices, making it unprofitable for low productivity firms to remain in the market. Because of the assumption of monopolistic competition and CES consumer preferences, optimal prices do not respond to the number of competing varieties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What actually does happen is entirely carried about in the labor market. The short description is that more productive firms now have access to more consumers, which makes them want to produce more, for which they need to hire more labor, which drives labor demand up, this increases the real wage, which makes it so less productive firms can no longer compete in the labor market.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>