<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sargent Reading Group Notes</title>
    <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Sargent Reading Group Notes</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-EN</language>
    <managingEditor>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</webMaster>
    <copyright>(c) 2015 Spencer Lyon.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://srg.spencerlyon.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Heathcote, Storesletten, and Violante (2017) (Optimal tax progressivity: An analytical framework)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/10/03/heathcote-storesletten-and-violante-2017-optimal-tax-progressivity-an-analytical-framework/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/10/03/heathcote-storesletten-and-violante-2017-optimal-tax-progressivity-an-analytical-framework/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The goal of this paper is to supply a theory that can shed light on what determines both the actual degree of tax progressivity in the US economy as well as a theoretical optimal level of tax progressivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;tax-function&#34;&gt;Tax function&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tax function used in this paper comes from Benabou (2002) and is log linear in income. That is taxes collected gross income, minus &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;λ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; times gross income to the &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;1 − &lt;em&gt;τ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;λ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; governs the average level of taxes and &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;τ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; controls the degree of progressivity. If &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;τ&lt;/em&gt; &amp;gt; 0&lt;/span&gt; the system is progressive and the marginal tax rate rises with income. If &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;τ&lt;/em&gt; &amp;lt; 0&lt;/span&gt; the system is regressive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although very simple, this tax function matches the US tax system quite well. The tax data used in the paper is produced by taking income data from the PSID and passing it to the NBER TAXSIM program. The authors then estimate &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;λ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;τ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; using ordinary least squares on the log of the tax function. The estimated value for &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;τ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; is &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;0.181&lt;/span&gt;, with a very small standard error. The R-squared for the regression 0.91, suggesting that the log-linear tax function is able to capture data quite well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;model&#34;&gt;Model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I now describe the model used by the authors to talk about the optimal degree of tax progressivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a unit mass of households. Each household survives from one period to the next with probability &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;δ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;. Each period a new cohort of households of mass &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;(1 − &lt;em&gt;δ&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; is born.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lifecycle of each agent starts with an initial investment in skills. Skills are chosen when the agent initially enters the economy, are fixed over time, and impact the earnings the individual earns each period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Output in the economy is formed using a CES technology over the average efficiency units of labor supplied by each skill type multiplied by the mass of agents with that skill type.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Output is used both for individual consumption and government spending.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Agents have preferences over the initial investment in skill, as well as consumption, labor supply, and government spending each working period. The disutility of the initial skill investment has the form of the CRRA utility function, augmented by an individual-specific multiplicative parameter that determines the idiosyncratic cost of acquiring skill. The per-period utility function is fully separable in time and all components: log in consumption and government spending and CRRA in labor supplied. The labor disutility term is also augmented by a multiplicative, idiosyncratic term capturing varying disutility of work. The two preference shocks are assumed to be normally distributed and independent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Log labor productivity is the sum of two terms: (1) a random walk and (2) purely transitory shocks. Individual earnings are the product of hours worked, labor productivity, and the price for a each worker&#39;s skill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are full insurance markets against the transitory shocks to labor productivity, but there is no insurance for the shocks to the permanent component. Insurance claims are in zero net supply and agents are born without any claims.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government has expenditures equal to a constant share of total output each period. They run a balanced budget, so the total net taxes collected must equal expenditures. The government is responsible for choosing the share of output used for government spending (call it &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;g&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;) and the tax progressivity parameter &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;τ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;. Given these two, the scale term in the tax function is set to ensure a balanced budget.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;equilibrium-and-social-welfare&#34;&gt;Equilibrium and social welfare&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government uses a utilitarian social welfare function to rank policies characterized by &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;(&lt;em&gt;g&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;τ&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; pairs. The government must balance a few competing forces when choosing a &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;(&lt;em&gt;g&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;τ&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; plan:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The utilitarian social welfare function causes the government to dislike inequality. A more progressive tax system lowers inequality.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Higher tax progressively distorts both the skill investment and labor supply choices, pushing both of them lower. This lowers aggregate output in the economy, which lowers the utility level of each agent, brining down social welfare.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;parameterization&#34;&gt;Parameterization&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors are able to solve model entirely in closed form. This allows them to derive closed form expressions for aggregate moments as a function of parameters that they then use to parameterize the model. They use data from the PSID and CEX and target variances and co-variances between wages, hours worked, and consumption to pin down parameter values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When choosing parameter values, the authors use their estimate for the progressivity of the US tax system and set &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;g&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; to 0.189 -- consistent with US levels of government spending over the same time horizon as the micro data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under this parameterization, they can then determine the optimal values of &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;τ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;g&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; within the model. The find that the optimal &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;τ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; implied by their model is 0.084, meaning the model suggests the tax system should be less progressive than what is observed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final thing I will talk about is how each component of their model contributes to this optimal number.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a representative agent version of the economy (variance of all idiosyncratic shocks is zero), the optimal value for &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;τ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; is -0.233.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After adding back just the heterogeneity in disutility in skill investment the optimal value for &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;τ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; moves to -0.035.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adding back heterogeneity in preferences moves &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;τ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; to -0.007.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also including the permanent, uninsurable labor productivity shocks moves &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;τ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; to 0.009.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally adding all back the transitory, insurable shocks returns tau to the baseline level of 0.084.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Antras, de Gortari, Itskhoki (2017) (Globalization, Inequality, and welfare)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/09/26/antras-de-gortari-itskhoki-2017-globalization-inequality-and-welfare/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/09/26/antras-de-gortari-itskhoki-2017-globalization-inequality-and-welfare/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The goal of this paper is to quantify the welfare implications of opening to trade in a setting where trade increases aggregate income, but also increases income inequality. Furthermore, redistribution happens through distorting income taxes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;closed-economy-model&#34;&gt;Closed economy model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discrete time, infinite horizon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A continuum of consumers, each with GHH preferences over an aggregate consumption good and labor. Individuals are indexed by their ability to produce a certain variety or task (unique to each consumer). Individual production or output is the product of ability and labor supply. The ability of each agent is fixed over time and drawn from a known distribution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tasks performed by all agents are imperfect substitutes and are combined in the production of an aggregate, final consumption good using a CES aggregator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Labor income is taxed according to a tax schedule that is log linear in individual production. There are no assets, so consumption each period is equal to after-tax income. The exponent on individual production indexes the progressivity of the tax system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government that collects taxes to finance exogenous government expenditures that are a constant share of total output. Government expenditures do not show up in individual utility The government runs a balanced budget each period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Individuals choose labor supply to solve a static utility maximization problem. The authors have closed form solutions for both optimal after-tax earnings and individual utility -- both indexed by the individual ability level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;measuring-welfare&#34;&gt;Measuring welfare&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors review two classic approaches to measuring welfare and then propose a new, third approach that mixes the previous two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We don&#39;t have time to review the former methods that serve as building blocks, so I&#39;ll just describe the novel method proposed and used by the authors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- The first is known as the Kaldor-Hicks compensation principle. The idea is that
for a pair of policies (call one the baseline and the other the alternative),
the researcher will compute a compensating or equivalent variation to
individual income that makes the agent indifferent between the baseline policy
and the alternative policy, with the added income. In this simple setting the
compensating variation sets utility of income under the baseline policy equal
to the utility of income plus the variation under the alternative policy.

One issue with this approach is that it makes three assumptions:

1. There is _potential_ for agents better off under the alternative policy to compensate the losers from the policy change
2. This _potential_ compensation actually takes place
3. The government (or central authority) has access to a non-distortionary means to actually implement this redistribution (e.g. they can use lump sum taxes).

The second approach is known as the welfarist approach. The key idea with this
approach is that there exists a social welfare function that maps a vector of
agents&#39; welfare levels into a single real number. The class of social welfare
functions typically chosen express social welfare as the integral over the
distribution of agent types of a concave transformation of actual disposable
income under a proposed policy. A popular choice of concave transformation is
to apply the CRRA utility function, where instead capturing risk aversion, the
parameter instead indexes inequality aversion.

In this setting, welfare can be written as the product aggregate output in the
economy and a function of expected earnings under the proposed distribution and
social welfare function parameters. The second term is referred to as the
_welfarist inequality correction_ by the authors. --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The core idea behind their approach has two components:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The government uses the progressive tax system to redistribute earnings across agents of differing ability levels. A more progressive tax system has two effects: (1) it compresses the after-tax income distribution, reducing inequality and (2) it distorts the labor supply decision, especially for high ability workers. This impacts aggregate income. This tradeoff captures costly-redistribution.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A CRRA-like social welfare function is used to map from the set of individual utilities into a single value for social welfare. The parameter in this function is not a risk aversion parameter in this setting, but rather an inequality aversion parameter.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the setting described above, the value for social welfare can be written as the product of three terms:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The counterfactual level of welfare in an economy with zero tax progressivity and zero inequality aversion&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A costly-redistribution correction that is a function of the elasticity of taxable realized income to the marginal tax rate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A welfarist correction that is a function of the inequality aversion parameter in the social welfare function and expected disposable income under a given policy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This decomposition highlights the core tension faced by the policy maker: how progressive should the tax system be in order to reduce inequality, keeping in mind that higher progressivity depresses aggregate output.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;some-data&#34;&gt;Some data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors look at some US data over the period 1979-2007 through their model. After calibration, their joint analysis of model and data leaves them with the following takeaways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tax progressivity steadily fell over the sample&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The costly redistribution correction has risen over time -- meaning it is getting closer to 1 and depressing aggregate welfare &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The welfarist correction fell sharply over the sample&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;trade&#34;&gt;Trade&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their main goal was to measure welfare in a setting with distiortionary redistribution and trade. To turn their model into a trade model they simply make &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;N&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; exact copies of the closed economy described above. Agents can supply their task to any country they want, but must pay costs to do so. There are both fixed costs that rise exponentially with the number of countries supplied and an iceberg cost meaning that only a fraction individual output reaches a foreign destination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They make a few other assumptions to ensure that all countries are symmetric.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are three main changes induced by opening the economy to trade:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Aggregate output rises -- the CES aggregator likes to have more varieties and now in addition to domestic inputs, there are foreign inputs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Welfare of &lt;em&gt;all agents&lt;/em&gt; increases. This happens because the greater number of varieties lowers the price of the final good and all agents are able to consume more.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Realized income inequality rises. This happens becuase the increase in realized income is not symmetric over the individual ability distribution. Only agents with high ability find it optimal to pay the costs to export their variety, so they end up with a larger increase in income than relatively less able agents.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key takeaway is that trade-induced increases in the dispersion of income reduce the gains from trade by about 20% (for a &lt;em&gt;plausable&lt;/em&gt; value of the inequality aversion parameter). Furthermore welfare gains are about 15% smaller when redistribution happens through distortionary means than it would be if lump-sum transfers could be used.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ljungqvist and Sargent (2011) (A Labor Supply Elasticity Accord?.)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/09/12/ljungqvist-and-sargent-2011-a-labor-supply-elasticity-accord./</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/09/12/ljungqvist-and-sargent-2011-a-labor-supply-elasticity-accord./</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here Ljungqvist and Sargent explain both sides of a long debated issue regarding labor supply elasticity (percent change in labor supply divided by percent change in wages) and then describe a relatively new idea that has the potential to reconcile the opposing views. The main argument from the micro-and-labor-economics camp is that the labor supply elasticity is quite low for individuals in the work force. On the other hand, macroeconomists typically say that the aggregate labor supply elasticity is large.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The classic way to reconcile these two seemingly opposing viewpoints is to allow labor supply to respond sharply on the &lt;em&gt;extensive&lt;/em&gt; margin. This will allow workers to continue to have a small elasticity while they are working, but as individuals move in and out of work more freely the aggregate labor supply elasticity is driven up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The benchmark way to model this flavor of environment is to follow Rogerson and use employment lotteries with perfect, competitive insurance markets for unemployment. The basic idea is that households are composed of families. Each family will choose a probability with which each of its members works in that period. If the realization of the lottery is positive, that individual supplies full labor to the market and receives wages. If the realization is negative they supply zero labor. The family then purchases an insurance claim that pays a specified amount of the consumption good if a member of the family receives a bad outcome from the employment lottery. The insurance market is competitive, which results in all agents having equal consumption after lotteries have been realized and insurance claims paid out. In this setting agents who work supply the maximum amount of labor regardless of the wage, meaning the micro labor supply elasticity is small. However as wages change, households will adjust the probability that each family member works, causing there to be some elasticity on the extensive margin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is commonly referred to as an aggregation theory. Micro economists have issue with this particular aggregation theory because they cannot find evidence that these sort of employment lotteries exist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ljungqvist and Sargent then go on to explain a new way of thinking that seeks to unify the rhetoric regarding labor supply elasticity. The main idea is that instead of thinking about the labor supply choice as a lottery played out amongst family members in a household, we can think of it as an individual making a binary labor supply decision at every instant of their life. One natural interpretation of this type of setting is that there is a lifecycle component to the model, where after some date agents enter retirement and do not supply labor any more, regardless of the wage. The fraction of the lifetime spent working has been termed the career length of the individual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turns out that for an interior solution for labor supply probability in the Rogerson model is identical to interior solutions for career length, when the discount factor equals the market rate of return in a deterministic setting. This means that same results for micro and macro labor supply elasticity that held in the Rogerson setting continue to hold in this lifecycle model. There are two last points I&#39;ll make about this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This type of aggregation theory has been better received by labor economists. They consider the career length choice more plausible than the employment lottery choice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This does not settle the debate about whether the macro (aggregate) labor supply elasticity should be large or small: the theory could support either argument.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recall that I said the lifecycle career-length choice was equivalent to the employment probability lottery, at &lt;em&gt;interior&lt;/em&gt; solutions. The behavior is somewhat different at the corners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For our discussion we can think of an agent being on corner solution as an agent who is incentivized to retire at a certain age. If a large portion of the workers in an economy are on a corner, then when wages move the aggregate response in labor supply will be dampened (people can&#39;t come out of retirement)) and the aggregate labor supply elasticity will be low. On the contrary, if there are relatively few agents at the corner, the aggregate labor supply elasticity will be high.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The measure of agents at a corner will be crucially impacted by the government policies regarding targeted retirement age, retirement benefits or payments, and how they are financed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ljungqvist and Sargent conclude by suggesting that a promising area for new research will look at how to reform taxation and disability/retirement payments to minimize the deadweight loss associated with distorting the labor supply decision through taxes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Autor, Dorn, Hanson, and Song (2014) (Trade Adjustment: Worker Level Evidence)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/05/02/autor-dorn-hanson-and-song-2014-trade-adjustment-worker-level-evidence/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/05/02/autor-dorn-hanson-and-song-2014-trade-adjustment-worker-level-evidence/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Empirical paper that tries to determine labor market response to China trade shock at the individual level. It is a complement to the authors&#39; China Syndrome paper that answers similar questions at the regional level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;stylized-facts&#34;&gt;Stylized facts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To prompt their research, the authors list a number of recent stylized facts concerning China&#39;s impact on US labor markets. They are that greater import exposure results in&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Higher rates of plant exit and more rapid declines in plant employment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Larger decreases in manufacturing employment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Increases in unemployment and labor force non-participation rates&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These facts have been verified or reproduced at the industry and regional level, but the gap that this paper seeks to fill is what are the associated facts at the individual level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specifically, the authors state their purpose as seeking to capture the changes in earnings and employments that workers in exposed industries encountered when adjusting to the trade shock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;theory&#34;&gt;Theory&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper does not do rigorous theoretical work, but they do paint the picture of the type of model they had in mind when they came up with their empirical specification. This is the setting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider an economy with two sectors -- one that is directly exposed to trade shocks and one that is not. In the long run, but not necessarily the short run, labor is between sectors such that long run wages are equalized across sectors for similarly skilled workers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suppose that foreign productivity growth causes demand for the home country&#39;s traded sector to fall. That sector begins contracting immediately, reducing their demand for labor which depresses wages. Depending on the degree of frictions to labor mobility, the transition of workers from the exposed sector to the unexposed sector may take time. Along this transition path, wages in the exposed sector will be below wages in the non-exposed sector. Summing worker earnings over the pre-shock, shock, and post-shock periods; cumulative income for workers initially employed in the exposed sector will be lower than workers who started in the other sector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These effects on cumulative earnings and the associated worker turnover across employees, sectors, and even regions, are the focus of the empirical study in this paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;data&#34;&gt;Data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To do their analysis, the authors use data in the period 1988-2007. The data come from from a few sources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The annual Employee-Employer File from the social security administration. This contains a randomly selected 1% of US workers and provides annual earnings, employer ID number, and SIC code for each job a worker held. This data is augmented with demographic data on each individual, also using data from the social security administration.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The County Business Patterns from the IRS provide aggregate estimates of employment by industry and county. This is used because the 1% sample does not have enough data to accurately portray the regional industry structure in the US&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Comtrade data is used to give an estimate of imports and exports at the HS-10 level. This data is aggregated to the industry level to be consistent with the other data used in this study.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;empirical-model&#34;&gt;Empirical model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main empirical model is a linear regression model that regresses&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the cumulative earnings for a worker on&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the change in import penetration from 1991-2007&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the level of import penetration in 1991&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;demographic controls for the individual&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;industry specific controls that capture the economic conditions in each industry in 1991.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their definition of industry import penetration is the change in imports from China over their time horizon divided by initial industry absorption, which they define as industry shipments, plus imports, less exports.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To address concerns that changes in import penetration are driven by a mixture of supply side effects in China &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; demand side shocks in the US, the authors instrument this variable using the same data from other high-income countries. The assumption with this instrument is high-income countries are similar exposed to growth in Chinese imports and that demand side shocks between the US and other high income countries are not correlated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main results are that there is a significant, negative effect of increased import penetration on individual cumulative earnings. More precisely, if we consider a worker in the 75% percentile of import penetration (about 7.3%) to a worker in the 25th percentile, the model predicts 20% lower cumulative earnings between 1991 and 2007.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These results are robust to alternative measures of worker earnings and the inclusion or exclusion of various control variables.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;worker-mobility&#34;&gt;Worker mobility&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other main empirical exercise is an attempt to determine the degree of worker mobility in response to the change in import penetration. The use of social security data enables tracking individuals over time to see the industry of their employer as well as their county of residence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here they run their same regression on different subsets of the data at a time:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;employees who stayed at the same firm for the entirety of the sample&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Employees who moved to another firm in the same industry&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Employees who moved to a firm in a different industry, within the manufacturing sector&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Workers who left manufacturing altogether&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Workers who moved to a firm that didn&#39;t have a registered industry (mostly new firms that the SSA didn&#39;t update their records to account for industry)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They find that workers who stayed at highly exposed firms suffered the largest decline in earnings. Workers who shifted firms did better. Others who shifted industries within manufacturing actually saw an increase in wages. Workers who left manufacturing suffered losses comparable to those who shifted firms within the same industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They interpret these findings as suggesting that workers who started at firms in highly exposed industries experience both reduced earnings at their initial employers and lower income from firms in the same industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They find that the negative effects on workers at firms in exposed industry is only partially offset by gains from workers in non-exposed industries. Their main explanation for this is that workers who leave an exposed firm seem to end up working at a different exposed firm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They also try to see if exposed workers offset the losses from trade via geographic mobility. Their results show little to no evidence of this happening within the their sample.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Greenland, Lopresti, McHenry (2016) (Import Competition and Internal Migration)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/04/25/greenland-lopresti-mchenry-2016-import-competition-and-internal-migration/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/04/25/greenland-lopresti-mchenry-2016-import-competition-and-internal-migration/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a purely empirical paper that tries to determine the degree to which there was worker relocation across regions in the US in response to the Chinese trade shock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many recent papers have documented negative regional labor market consequences in regions that specialize in industries that are more exposed to Chinese trade competition. Among these results are higher unemployment, lower wages, and lower labor force participation rates. Furthermore, evidence has been presented showing that there was little to no contemporaneous worker migration out of exposed regions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main finding of this paper is that regions at the 75th percentile of import exposure had population growth 2.1% lower than regions at the 25th percentile of exposure. Additionally, the majority of these migrations occurred between 7 and 10 years &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; the onset of the China import shock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;data&#34;&gt;Data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story is that before 2001 China was paying the normal trade relation tariffs, but on a potentially temporary basis. This is the tariff rate paid amongst all WTO nations. Each year the US congress would vote to decide if China would be granted the same tariff rates in the next year, or if they would rise above the WTO levels. This created uncertainty for Chinese firms about future costs. In 2001 congress decided to give China WTO tariff rates permanently, thus resolving the uncertainty. The data shows a sharp uptick in US imports from China, suggesting that many firms chose to enter in response to lower uncertainty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors leverage this fact to construct their measure of import exposure to Chinese trade across regions in the US. Specifically, for each industry (not region) they construct a tariff gap, which is the difference between potential non-WTO tariff rates and WTO tariff rates within the industry. The next step is to map this into a regional measure, at the commuting zone level. A commuting zone is a notion of local economy, constructed so that it if an individual lives in a commuting zone, it is very likely that their day to day job is also in the commuting zone. To construct a regional tariff gap they compute an industry-labor-share weighed average of the tariff gap across all industries that operate in each commute zone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors then use data from the US census to construct population totals in each commute zone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors also do some work at the individual level using data from the National Education Longitudinal Study, but the results are secondary to the ones presented at the aggregate level, so I will not talk about them here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- The final main source of data comes From the National Education Longitudinal
Study of 1988 and 2002. This data set constructs a nationally-representative
sample of 10th graders, providing information in location, demographics, and
educational outcomes. 10 years after the initial survey, there is a follow-up
survey that reports the location of main residence for all the original
participants. This allows the authors to track the migration patterns at the
individual level, with additional data on demographics and educational outcomes. --&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;regression-model&#34;&gt;Regression Model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main results of the paper are regression outcomes from regressing the 10-year change in log population in a commute zone on&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;an interaction between the tariff gap in the commute zone and an indicator for whether or not the time period is after 2001,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Time invariant regional controls, interacted with the post-WTO rates indicator&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A time fixed effect&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without the inclusion of the regional control variables, the regression predicts a small and statistically insignificant change in population in response to an interquartile shift in the tariff gap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, with the inclusion of the regional controls, the regression predicts that the interquartile effect of tariff gap on population growth is 2.1% -- significant at the 1% level. To me, this suggests that the controls that are included in the regression are &lt;em&gt;crucial&lt;/em&gt; for obtaining the results. Unfortunately the lack of a theoretical model means that the choice of which control variables are included is ad-hoc. A useful extension or follow up to this work would be to build a model that allows regional migration in response to trade shocks and let the model be informative about which control variables should be included.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FWIW the controls they included were the pre-1990 cz pop growth trend, share of population under 25 years old, share of population accounted for by minority groups&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;temporal-structure-of-migration&#34;&gt;Temporal structure of migration&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because these regressions were run using data between 1988-1998 and then 2002-2012, the results suggest only that within an 11 year window after China was granted permanent WTO tariff rates did this migration occur. The authors want to be able to answer the question &amp;quot;when in this 11 year window did the movement of workers happen?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To do this they use data data the US population migration data from the IRS. This data set uses the tax filings from individuals to determine, year to year, how many individuals moved from one county to another based on their primary residence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They use this data to regress the annual log change in commute zone population on&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;0 to 12 year changes in the tariff gap interacted with a post 2001 indicator&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;time invariant regional controls, interacted with the post 2001 indicator&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A commute zone fixed effect&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A time fixed effect&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The identification is weak of all 13 time-lag parameters, so they constrain the model so that the coefficients to evolve smoothly over time according to a cubic function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To do this they say that the point estimate for the lag l coefficient is equal to a cubic polynomial in l. They then construct 4 auxiliary variables that are the sum of lagged changes from 0 to 12 of the tariff gap times post 2001 dummy times the number of lags to the [0, 1, 2, 3] (that&#39;s where they get 4 variables). They then replace the 13 lag terms with these 4 auxiliary variables and estimate coefficients on just the 4 parameters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This reduces the number of parameters from 13 to 4. Model predictions are largely unchanged, but identification is much sharper. Their results predict that about 20% of the total effect happens within one year of the trade shock, with a significant portion happening at a lag of 7 or more years (they don&#39;t give numbers...).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Galle, Rodriguez-Clare, and  Yi (2015) (Slicing the pie: Quantifying the aggregate and distributional effects of trade)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/03/07/galle-rodriguez-clare-and--yi-2015-slicing-the-pie-quantifying-the-aggregate-and-distributional-effects-of-trade/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/03/07/galle-rodriguez-clare-and--yi-2015-slicing-the-pie-quantifying-the-aggregate-and-distributional-effects-of-trade/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This paper develops a model that allows the authors to assess the aggregate gains from trade and the distribution of the gains from trade across groups of workers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The motivation for the paper came from a recognition that most empirical work focuses on the losses accrued on the import side from increased competition. The general equilibrium setup in this paper captures both import and export effects of trade shocks, which they use to paint a more complete picture of the distribution of welfare responses to trade exposure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;model&#34;&gt;Model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The model is a mashup between the Eaton and Kortum model of international trade and the Roy model of worker heterogeneity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firms:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;N&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; countries and &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; sectors within each country&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Within each sector there is a continuum of goods produced by firms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Each firm has an idiosyncratic productivity, drawn from a Frechet distribution. Output is productivity times labor efficiency units hired&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All goods within each sector are aggregated with a CES technology.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The sectoral outputs are aggregated with a Cobb-Douglass technology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are iceberg trade costs to trade goods internationally&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All technology and preference parameters are country specific&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Households:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;G&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; types of workers, where the types differ in their ability across sectors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Each worker type draws efficiency units for each sector from a Frechet distribution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Workers supply labor inelastically&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!-- The authors note under extreme parameter assumptions, this model nests other
recent models. --&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;equilibrium&#34;&gt;Equilibrium&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Workers are heterogenous in sector productivities, but not across groups. This means that sectoral labor supply is upward sloping and wages will differ across sectors, but be constant across groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An equilibrium will be pinned down by a set of country-sector specific wages that allow labor markets to clear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each country-sector labor market clearing condition equates the demand for efficiency units of labor from the firms with the supply of these units from households.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;trade-shock&#34;&gt;Trade shock&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main welfare measure used in this paper is real income within a country and group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A trade shock is modeled as a change in iceberg trade costs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In response to a trade shock, the change in welfare for a particular group is decomposed into two components:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The product of changes to home-to-home trade shares across sectors. This term is found in multi-sectoral Eaton and Kortum models.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The product of changes to group-level employment shares, across sectors. This term is new to this model and is the emphasis of their analysis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To understand this second term, they write it as a function of the Kullback-Leibler divergence. This divergence is used as a way to summarize the degree of specialization of a group. The divergence of one vector &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; from another vector &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;y&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; is the sum of &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;y&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; times the log difference of &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;y&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They can write this second term as the exponential of the difference in Kullback-Leibler divergence between post-trade shock employment shares and the Cobb Douglass sectoral weights and the pre-trade shock KL divergence between the same vectors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Viewing this term in this light makes it very clear that the welfare effect of a trade shock on a particular group is determined by the change in the degree of the specialization of that group across sectors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aggregate welfare change in response to the trade shock is the sum over the group-specific welfare changes, weighted by the each group&amp;rsquo;s share of aggregate income.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This differs from the multi-sectoral Eaton and Kortum models because the trade shock will impact wages, which feeds back into group level income and sectoral level prices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;distribution-of-welfare-responses&#34;&gt;Distribution of welfare responses&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of the paper was to look at the distribution of welfare changes across worker groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In experiments where the economy goes from autarky (iceberg costs at infinity) to trading with the world, they find the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Worker groups whose comparative advantage is in import-intensive sectors suffer welfare losses&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On the other hand, welfare rises for worker groups that specialize in export-intensive sectors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The net gain from opening to trade is positive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The degree of worker heterogeneity (one of the Frechet parameters for the distribution of worker efficiency) scales the aggregate gains from trade.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Autor, Dorn, and Hanson (2016) (The China Shock: Learning from Labor-Market Adjustment to Large Changes in Trade)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/02/28/autor-dorn-and-hanson-2016-the-china-shock-learning-from-labor-market-adjustment-to-large-changes-in-trade/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/02/28/autor-dorn-and-hanson-2016-the-china-shock-learning-from-labor-market-adjustment-to-large-changes-in-trade/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Review paper that summarizes the main points of the story behind China&#39;s fantastic growth in export markets in the lats 30 years and how it has impacted labor markets of developed countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper covers a width breadth of material in relatively little depth, so I will pick and choose from the main points they tried to make.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-story&#34;&gt;The story&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mao Zedong founded People&#39;s republic of China and governed it as the chairman of the communist part of China from 1949 until his death in 1976. He instituted many policies that lead to stagnating economic growth in China. From 1952 to 1978 China fell from being ranked 59th to 134th in GDP per capita out of the 167 Penn World Table countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following the death of Mao, Deng Xiaoping took over leading the People&#39;s republic and kicked off a decade of quote &amp;quot;reform and opening&amp;quot;. In 1992 he launched the &amp;quot;Southern Tour&amp;quot;, which included the creation of special economic zones (SEZ).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the early 1990&#39;s China began to create Special economic zones (SEZ). An SEZ allows foreign countries to set up factories that imported inputs and exported final outputs with relatively little interference from the government. Essentially it allows foreign firms to use Chinese labor for goods they sell outside of China. There were 20 SEZs in 1991 and 150 in 2010. The world bank estimates that GDI was 0.7% of Chinese GDP in 1980 and up to 4.2% in the 1990s and 2000s. Also, China&#39;s share of global manufacturing exports rose from 2.3% in 1991 to 18.8% in 2013.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;China&#39;s ascension into the modern trade network serves as a natural experiment that is exciting to economists for at least the following reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;China plays a quantitatively significant role in today&#39;s Global economy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The export growth was unexpected&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;China&#39;s isolation under Mao created a lot of room for China to catch up&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;China has a distinctive comparative advantage in manufacturing. This means China&#39;s growth in manufacturing exports led to a large positive shock in global manufacturing supply and a large negative global demand shock for raw materials.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;labor-market-effects&#34;&gt;Labor market effects&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The focus of the paper is how the increase in manufacturing exports from China impact labor markets. The authors review many papers and describe the empirical facts the literature has uncovered. I&#39;ll summarize the most salient ones here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early (2006) work documented industries facing greater increases in trade exposure are subject to higher rates of plant exit. Surviving plants have in more exposed regions have larger reductions in employment and a higher likelihood of adjusting their 4-digit manufacturing industry. I&#39;ll summarize the key empirical facts this paper documents in question and answer form:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A $1,000 increaser in a commute zone&#39;s per-worker import exposure reduces the fraction of working age population employed in manufacturing by 0.60 percentage points and raises the fraction of unemployed or out of the labor force by 0.22 percentage points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Acemoglu et. al. (2016) estimate that had import penetration from China not grown after 1999 there would have been 560,000 fewer manufacturing jobs lost through 1999 to 2011 (about 10% of job loss in that period). This is done using just a direct effect of foreign competition on exposed regions, but ignores input-ouput linkages to other firms in that region. Including IO linkages within the region drives that number to 2,000,000.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tracing individual workers over time shows there is little migration in response to the trade shock. The losses are localized and persistent and offsetting gains haven&#39;t been measured.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is other empirical work that shows that more trade-exposed commute zones experience larger reductions in average weekly wages. This result is extended using quintile regressions to account for the income distribution and the result is that the wage losses from trade exposure are concentrated in the bottom 4 wage deciles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Comparing the 25th and 75th percentiles of import exposure, individuals in the more exposed location experienced a reduction in annual labor income of $549 per adult. At the same time transfers to these individuals rose by $58, offsetting only about 10% of the losses.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Drozd &amp; Nozal(2012) (Understanding International Prices: Customers as Capital)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/02/28/drozd--nozal2012-understanding-international-prices-customers-as-capital/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/02/28/drozd--nozal2012-understanding-international-prices-customers-as-capital/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This paper builds a model that treats consumers as a form of non-productive capital in an attempt to resolve a few outstanding puzzles in the international macro literature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;puzzles&#34;&gt;Puzzles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The puzzles are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the standard theory (like BKK), the price of exported goods co-moves negatively with the price of imported goods. In their sample o2 12 OECD countries, the authors find that the correlation is always positive and covers a range from 0.57 to 0.94, with a median of 0.87.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Standard theory predicts that the volatility of the terms of trade (ratio of import to export price) and the real exchange rate is exactly the same. In their data sample, the ratio of these volatilities range from 0.21 to 0.83.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finally, there is a lot of empirical evidence of pricing to market &amp;ndash; an apparent violation of the law of one price (LOP). Standard theory suggests that the LOP always holds.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;model&#34;&gt;Model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Environment:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Discrete time, infinite horizon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Two ex-ante identical, symmetric countries called home and foreign&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The only source of uncertainty is country-specific productivity shocks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tradable goods are country specific and are produced using a CRS technology in capital and labor, subject to a productivity that is AR(1) in logs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Producers sell their goods to retailers in each country, then retailers sell the goods to final consumers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Households:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In each country there is a unit mass of identical households&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Each period they choose the level of consumption, investment physical capital, labor supply, purchase of tradable goods from domestic and foreign sources, and a portfolio from a complete set of one period state-contingent bonds to maximize the expected discounted lifetime utility from consumption and leisure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Domestic and foreign goods are combined with a CES technology with home bias. The aggregate is then allocated across consumption and investment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Producers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The novel part of this model is that producers must make costly matches with retailers in each country in order to sell their goods.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To do this the authors introduce two additional variables into an otherwise standard firm problem: marketing capital and a customer list &amp;ndash; both are market specific.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Marketing capital is non-productive, but is required for matching with new retailers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The customer list is the total number of matches a producer has made in that market. It is assumed that the producer can sell one unit of their output to each retailer in their customer list.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The customer list depreciates at a constant rate and is increased each period by the measure of searching retailers times this producer&amp;rsquo;s share of the marketing capital in the destination market.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The marketing capital depreciates at a constant rate, and is increased each period by direct marketing input less a fixed cost of adjusting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The firm takes as given his productivity state, level marketing capital and customer list in each market and chooses capital, labor, and marketing input to maximize the expected discounted value of profit streams.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Retailers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In each country there is an atomless retailers that purchase goods from producers and resell them to consumers in a destination-specific competitive market.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They face a cost of entry and dynamics are governed by a free entry condition&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When a retailer meets a producer, they bargain over the total surplus from a potential match. The surplus is split with a Nash bargaining solution with continuous renegotiation. The solution is a constant share of the surplus going to producers and retailers each period.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This model is able to resolve all three puzzles simultaneously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main result is that in this model, deviations from the law of one price are driven by movement in the real exchange rate. Here&amp;rsquo;s the main mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The real exchange rate moves when firms get a productivity shock relative to its competitors. In this case they will find it optimal to add new buyers when the surplus from trading is higher in one market than the other (they want to equate these). But, because there are adjustment costs, firms don&amp;rsquo;t equate these in one period, so there is a sustained short and medium run price differential. Along this transition the real exchange rate is moving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To understand the intuition behind these responses, consider the sequence of the events that follows the productivity shock. From panel A, observe that the domestic production cost v falls, which, ceteris paribus, must raise the surplus from trading the domestic good in matches. Second, due to home-bias in trade, relative to the foreign country retailers, the domestic country retailers have an advantage in meeting the domestic country producers. Not surprisingly, this creates a gap in the relative search intensity, which leads to the real exchange rate depreciation (this last implication follows from risk sharing condition). The price differential created by that feeds into prices at which producers sell to retailers and creates an incentive for the domestic country producers to expand their market share abroad more than at home. However, as implied by Lemma 1, in the short- and medium- run the adjustment of market shares will not close the initial price gap completely due to increasing cost of matching. As a result, the equilibrium response of prices features persistent deviations from LOP in our model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Barrot, Loualiche, Plosser, Sauvangnat (2016) (Import Competition and Household Debt)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/02/21/barrot-loualiche-plosser-sauvangnat-2016-import-competition-and-household-debt/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/02/21/barrot-loualiche-plosser-sauvangnat-2016-import-competition-and-household-debt/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Empirical paper that tries to quantify the effect of import competition on the composition of the balance sheet of individuals between 2000 and 2007.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main finding is that consumers in regions with higher exposure to import competition had debt growth of 20 percentage points more than consumers in regions with low import competition exposure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;data&#34;&gt;Data&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New york FRB consumer credit panel: 5% of all US individuals with a credit record and social security number. Data is measured at a quarterly frequency. The important features for this study are a breakdown of household debt into mortgages, home equity credit, auto loans, credit card debt, and other loans. There is also limited demographic data such as the age, credit score, and zip code of participants.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Census and IRS data to compute regional demographics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;House prices from CoreLogic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Employment data from BLS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Home Mortgage Disclosure Act data. the consumer credit panel doesn&amp;rsquo;t show what people did with rising debt. The authors here adopt the methodology explained in the paper Don presented last week&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PSID: track household income and debt over time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Building Permits survey BPS: capture change in mortgages due to new house purchases&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Peter Schott&amp;rsquo;s database of shipping costs as a percentage of sale price at the product level&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;strategy&#34;&gt;Strategy&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Benhabib, Perla, Tonetti (2017) (Reconciling Models of Diffusion and Innovation: A Theory of the Productivity Distribution and Technology Frontier.)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/02/14/benhabib-perla-tonetti-2017-reconciling-models-of-diffusion-and-innovation-a-theory-of-the-productivity-distribution-and-technology-frontier./</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/02/14/benhabib-perla-tonetti-2017-reconciling-models-of-diffusion-and-innovation-a-theory-of-the-productivity-distribution-and-technology-frontier./</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The main contribution of this paper is to provide a model where technology adoption and innovation interact to determine the equilibrium characteristics of the economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They end up using a model where adoption an the rate of innovation are both choice variables for the firm, but describe the main mechanisms and intuitions where only adoption is a control variable and innovation is stochastic. The qualitative results from both models are the same, so I to will use the simpler model with exogenous innovation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;model&#34;&gt;Model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Continuous time, infinite horizon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A continuum of firms produce a homogenous good. Firms are indexed by their productivity and their innovation ability. The production technology is equal to productivity. Innovation ability can either be high or low. Whenever innovation ability is high, productivity grows at a constant rate. When ability is low, there is no productivity growth. Transitions between high and low ability states occur randomly at a fixed rate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each period a firm has the option to adpot a new technology. When adoption takes place, innovation ability is reset to be low and productivity is drawn from the current distribution of productivity in the economy. Firms disount the future at a constant rate and choose only whether or not to adpot a new technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consumers&lt;/strong&gt; All the firms in the economy are owned by a representative consumer who has log preferences over aggregate consumption and discounts the future at a constant rate. The consumer makes no decisions and just serves as a way to measure welfare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors describe a balanced growth path equilibrium. Dividing by the growth rate of the economy allows us to think of this in terms of a stationary equilibrium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll describe the main results in question and answer form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;growth-rates&#34;&gt;Growth rates&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, does the optimal adoption policy influence the long run growth rate of the economy?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Answer:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It depends on how the option value adoption impacts the incentive to innovate. The policy dictates that firms at the bottom of the productivity distribution will adopt a new techonlogy and get a higher productivity. Firms in the upper tail of the productivity distribution will not choose to adopt a new technology. The growth rate of the economy is intimately related to the constant rate of innovation for high ability firms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key margin governing whether or not the adoption policy influences the long run growth rate of the economy is how high the option value of adopting is for medimum to high productivity firms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In calibrations of the model where the distribution of productivity is infinite or unbounded, the productivity difference between frontier firms and potential adopters is very large &amp;ndash; giving almost no option value for high productivity firms. This means that the long run growth rate will not&lt;br /&gt;
be impacted by adoption. However, if the support of productivity is bounded, then the option value is non-trivial, so adoption rates will determine growth rates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s more poignant in models where innovation rates are endogenous, but we kinda have a discrete version of that right now where firms can choose to adopt, which means they voluntarily leave the innovation state (and might get a draw that puts them back in it).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;productivity-distribution-shape&#34;&gt;Productivity distribution shape&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, how do adoption and innovation shape the stationary distribution of productivity?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along a balanced growth path, high innovative, high productivity firms will push the productivity frontier. This lengthens the right tail of the productivity distribution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adoption, on the other hand, is done by firms in the low end of the productivity distribution and acts as a way to redistribute these firms back towards the center of the distribution. Thus, adoption causes the distribution of productivity to contract and become more peaked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The overall shape of stationary distribution of de-trended productivity will be determined by how these forces compete.&lt;/p&gt;
&amp;lt;!&amp;mdash;
In calibrations where the support
of productivity is infinite, there are a continuum of equilibria featuring
fat-tails in the productivity distribution indexed by the thickness of the
tail (for each shape paramater there is an equilibrium growth rate strictly
greater than the innovation rate).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the support of z is unbounded, but finite, there is a unique equilibrium
where the growth rate of the economy is equal to the innovation rate. In this
setting, the adoption policy
&amp;ndash;&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Faber, Fally (2017) (Firm Heterogeneity in Consumption Baskets -- Evidence from Home and Store Scanner Data.)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/02/07/faber-fally-2017-firm-heterogeneity-in-consumption-baskets----evidence-from-home-and-store-scanner-data./</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/02/07/faber-fally-2017-firm-heterogeneity-in-consumption-baskets----evidence-from-home-and-store-scanner-data./</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This paper considers the relation between of firm size heterogeneity and income dispersion. Using two large panel data sets, they document a number of empirical facts about the link between these forms of heterogeneity, then build a model combining non-homothetic preferences for consumers and a Metliz&#39; style production environment that can match the facts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;data&#34;&gt;Data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kilts Nielsen consumer panel and retail scanner data..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;weekly upc code level data from households and firms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;contains prices and quantities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;also demographic info about households: discrete income binning, location&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Metadata about stores: brands they sell, location&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;empirical-finding&#34;&gt;Empirical finding&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Main empirical finding is that wealthier households spend a higher share of consumption expenditure on goods from large firms. The relationship is monotonic across the income distribution. Finding is robust across level of aggregation (product level, product module level, aggregate spending, etc.) and time frame (6 month windows or across entire sample)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;model&#34;&gt;Model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TODO&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;equilibrium&#34;&gt;Equilibrium&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TODO&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;counter-factuals&#34;&gt;counter factuals&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SEE NOTES IN PDF&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Y Yedid-Levi, S Haller, and D Fitzgerald (2017) (How Exporters Grow)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/01/31/y-yedid-levi-s-haller-and-d-fitzgerald-2017-how-exporters-grow/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2017/01/31/y-yedid-levi-s-haller-and-d-fitzgerald-2017-how-exporters-grow/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The authors of this paper use confidential Irish data to document 4 novel facts about the lifecycle of exporting firms and then combine two existing modeling pieces to builds a partial equilibrium model that can reconcile the reported facts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;data&#34;&gt;Data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors use two confidential micro data sets from Ireland:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Irish census of industrial production&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Irish custom records&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They are able to link the datasets to build a panel dataset at the firm-product-destination market level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;empirics&#34;&gt;Empirics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main empirical exercise is to determine how one of log revenue, log quantity, or log price varies with both the firm-product duration in a particular market and the length of a firm-product-market export spell. The export spell is defined as the number of consecutive periods a firm exports a particular product to a particular market. Note that in the regressions this is a constant number for the entire spell, while the export tenure rises from 1 to the duration of the spell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors also control for destination market fixed effects and firm-product-year fixed effects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are 4 key results from the estimation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quantities grow dramatically in the first five years of successful export spells, defined as spells that last at least seven years. This growth is statistically significant up to a horizon of four years and is not driven purely by part-year effects in the first year (i.e. there is economically and statistically significant growth between years 2 and 4).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Within successful export spells, there are no statistically or economically significant dynamics in prices.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Higher initial quantities predict longer export spells: for spells lasting between one and four years, all pairwise comparisons of initial quantities are statistically different.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Initial prices do not predict export spell length.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors do a number of robustness checks and report that the results are qualitatively unchanged when the data is cut differently or other controls are used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;model&#34;&gt;Model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I now turn to the model. The use of the model is not as interesting or enlightening as the components themselves, so I will focus my discussion on why they made the assumptions they did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors make a quick note that common supply-side tricks for generating revenue and size dynamics (productivity shocks, capital adjustment costs, capacity or financial constraints, market-specific cost shocks, etc.) have a difficult time generating the observed dynamics in quantity without introducing dynamics in prices. For this reason they choose to focus on demand-side features that can generate dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They choose two of the more common demand side bells and whistles to include in their model:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learning about unobserved idiosyncratic shocks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consumer capital: firms build up a consumer base that deprecates over time and add consumers by direct investment in marketing or other costly acquisition methods.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After estimating the model with simulated method of moments (targeting moments about revenues and quantities over export spells), the authors show that the model can match all 4 of the key facts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They also show that both learning and consumer capital are necessary in their framework. To do this they remove one at a time, re-estimate the model, and show that the model generates price dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lustig, Zhang, and Hartman-Glaser (2016) (Capital Share Dynamics When Firms Insure Managers)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/12/13/lustig-zhang-and-hartman-glaser-2016-capital-share-dynamics-when-firms-insure-managers/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/12/13/lustig-zhang-and-hartman-glaser-2016-capital-share-dynamics-when-firms-insure-managers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This paper uses Compustat data to document that the aggregate capital share of income and average capital share of income have diverged over the last 20 years. Specifically, the average capital share has fallen while the aggregate share has risen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They then write down a model that uses changes in firm level volatility of productivity to generate similar dynamics in general equilibrium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The model is interesting in its own right. It features a 2 sided limited commitment contracting problem. The agent has all bargaining power ex ante, but after the principal faces idiosyncratic shocks he ends up with capturing almost all aggregate rents ex post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is related to a new literature on carefully modeling large firms in order to understand aggregates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;model&#34;&gt;Model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The model is set in continuous time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unit measure of ex ante identical firms. Each firm has an idiosyncratic time-varying productivity. Firms are owned by risk neutral investors (or shareholders) and operated by skilled managers. Firms rent physical capital and employ unskilled labor to produce using a decreasing returns to scale production technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firm productivity evolves as a geometric brownian motion that is subject to a negative poisson shock. If productivity reaches a strictly positive minimum value (determined in equilibrium), or if poisson process jumps, the firm exits immediately. There is a competitive fringe of potential entrants. When an investor creates a new firm they pay a fixed cost &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;P&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;. Each period firms enter until the expected value of entering is equal to &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;P&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; (free entry). After entering the initial productivity level is drawn from a Pareto distribution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a firm is formed, but before initial productivity is realized, the investor is matched with a risk adverse manager and the investor offers a long term contract. The contract is a sequence of payments to be made to the manager at each instant. The manager has convex preferences over this sequence of payments and discounts the future at a constant rate. The manager can choose to accept or reject the proposed contract. Upon rejection the manager is immediately matched with a new potential entrant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both parties are free to terminate the contract at any time. If the manager walks away from the firm, he will receive some outside option that is determined in equilibrium. The investor will choose to continue operations as long there is a positive net present value. The investor faces an optimal stopping time problem that characterizes when the firm is abandoned. The abandonment problem is to maximize the present discounted value of profits less managerial payments from the current period until the random stopping time, subject to the constraint that the manager doesn&#39;t walk away. The constraint sets the NPV of managerial payments plus post-stopping value equal to the outside option. This constraint is always binding, so WLOG the authors restrict attention to contracts that gives the manager a fixed payment until the firm exits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;equilibrium&#34;&gt;Equilibrium&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors use this model to describe how to match the facts about the capital share of income. The main mechanism is that an increase in the volatility parameter in the productivity process will do two main things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;raise the real option value of waiting to abandon for firms with low productivity. This results in a decrease in the lower productivity threshold at which firms exit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Increase the number of firms with very high productivity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, higher volatility in innovations to productivity creates fat tails in the distribution of productivity across firms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The average capital share of income is computed as the integral of profits less managerial payments divided by profits over all firms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aggregate capital share of income is computed as the integral of profits less managerial payments over all firms divided by the integral of profits over all firms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fat right tail will put more mass on the extremely productive firms who are earning profits far above the managerial payments. This drives up the aggregate capital share of income.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, the additional mass of low productivity firms will bring the average capital share of income down.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Timoshenko (2015) (Learning, prices, and firm dynamics)</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/12/06/timoshenko-2015-learning-prices-and-firm-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/12/06/timoshenko-2015-learning-prices-and-firm-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The authors of this paper use firm level data on Portuguese manufacturing firms and documents two new novel facts about the joint evolution of firm performance and prices:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Within product categories, firms with longer tenure in export markets tend to export larger quantities at similar prices&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Older or more experienced exporters tend to import more expensive inputs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors then write down a model that can match these facts&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;model&#34;&gt;Model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time is discrete, there are N countries. Each country is populated by a unit mass of infinitely lived consumers. There re two sectors in each economy: a final goods sector and an intermediate inputs sector. The final goods sector is populated by a mass of monopolistically competitive firms that each supply a differentiated variety of varying quality. The intermediate inputs sector is perfectly competitive and operates with a CRS production technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consumers have log preferences over a CES aggregation of final goods. Within the CES aggregator final good has a multiplicative term representing the firm chosen quality of the good as well as a multiplicative preference shock term. This is idiosyncratic across firms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TODO: DESCRIBE WHAT THE STRUCTURE IS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;intermediate-sector&#34;&gt;intermediate sector&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perfect competition leads to price being equal to marginal cost&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;final-goods&#34;&gt;final goods&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Static problem: choose good quality and quantity based on expected profits in each economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Entry problem: given result of static problem, firms choose each period which markets to enter. If they enter they pay a fixed cost per market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For each market the firm serves, they observe the equilibrium price that cleared the market for their good. They invert this price to uncover what the demand shock was in that period. They use this demand shock as a noisy signal though which they update their beliefs about the distribution of demand shocks they face.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;eqm&#34;&gt;eqm&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They show that this model can generate dynamics that match the two empirical facts from before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;counterfactual&#34;&gt;Counterfactual&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They also do a very brief counterfactual exercise where they consider the welfare implications of imposing a minimum quality standard on all exported goods. They find that this limit decreases welfare. The mechanism is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;quality standard raises productivity threshold for entry into export market&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The decline in number of exporters reduces competition in each market, raising prices&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Another effect is less foreign firms allows for more low efficiency domestic firms to enter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is also an impact on the intensive margin:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;firms close to the productivity threshold (small or young) will face a binding quality constraint&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;in order to export these firms must comply and in order to do so they need to pick which quality intermediate inputs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;higher quality inputs requires more labor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This leads in a reallocation of resources among exporters toward young and small firms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TODO FILL THIS IN!!!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hess:2000wh (Risk sharing by households within and across regions and industries. (Hess, Shin; 2000))</title>
      <link>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/11/22/hess2000wh-risk-sharing-by-households-within-and-across-regions-and-industries.-hess-shin-2000/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>spencer.lyon@stern.nyu.edu (Spencer Lyon)</author>
      <guid>http://srg.spencerlyon.com/2016/11/22/hess2000wh-risk-sharing-by-households-within-and-across-regions-and-industries.-hess-shin-2000/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The goal of this paper is to test the degree of risk sharing across regions and industries in the US.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rough outline is to write down a simple model they use to motivate an empirical specification, then test if that specification holds in the data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;model&#34;&gt;Model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are H households that each live in one of R regions and work within one of I industries. Each period, households receive an endowment of the consumption good and are able to trade in complete state contingent markets. Households have time-separable CRRA preferences that are subject to multiplicative preference shocks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors formulate the social planner&amp;rsquo;s problem for the entire economy. The first order condition for each household equates the Lagrange multiplier on the resource constraint to the Pareto weight times marginal utility of consumption.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They then take logs, sum across all households, and take first differences to obtain a key equation that says household log consumption growth is equal to aggregate log consumption growth plus the difference in deviations of individual preference shocks from the average preference shock times a scale factor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two key things to understand about this relationship:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is perfect within period risk sharing across households as their consumption is independent of their endowment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is also intertemporal consumption smoothing because the innovation to permanent income is the same across households because it is linked to aggregate consumption growth. When solving the planner&amp;rsquo;s problem it is difficult to write down the permanent income process, but that&amp;rsquo;s how it works.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They also consider market structures where there is perfect risk sharing only within a region or within an industry, but not across these groups. They solve for allocations in the within-group risk sharing economy using a social planner problem, just like before. The only difference is that the new planners only consider the agents in one group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The optimality conditions are identical and that important equation relates individual consumption growth to group-wise aggregate consumption growth and preference shocks is the same. If you then aggregate these within-group conditions across the groups you arrive at the same condition we got at the end of the economy-wide planner&amp;rsquo;s problem, with the addition of one extra term. This term is a risk adjusted difference in group and economy Lagrange multipliers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to derive the equation they use as the main specification for the empirical exercises, they need to remove these unobservable Lagrange multipliers. To do this they return one more time to optimality conditions for the different planners and manipulate them to write the difference in Lagrange multipliers as the difference in group and economy level consumption growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;empirics&#34;&gt;Empirics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final equation they end up taking to the data is that individual log consumption growth is equal to the sum of aggregate log consumption growth, the difference between regional and aggregate consumption growth, the difference between industry and aggregate consumption growth, controls for changes in preferences, and individual income growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They use data from the PSID to run regressions on this model. The theory suggests that if there is complete risk sharing across regions and industries, that the coefficients on those terms should be zero. They find that these coefficients are significantly different from zero, suggesting that a large fraction of wealth is incompletely shared across regions and industries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- The LHS of the economy wide and group specific equations is individual
consumption growth, which allows them to write the difference between economy
level and within group aggregate consumption as a statement about individual
preference shocks. Applying a law of large numbers will cause these individual
deviations from aggregate preference shocks to aggregate out and the
implication is that economy wide an within group consumption growth should be
the same. --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>